<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A familiar guide to the right and profitable receiving of the Lord's Supper wherein also the way and method of our salvation is briefly and plainly declar'd / by Theophilus Dorrington.</title>
            <author>Dorrington, Theophilus, d. 1715.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 198 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 106 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A36365</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1936</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12791</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12334275</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12334275</idno>
            <idno type="VID">59728</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A36365)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59728)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 208:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A familiar guide to the right and profitable receiving of the Lord's Supper wherein also the way and method of our salvation is briefly and plainly declar'd / by Theophilus Dorrington.</title>
                  <author>Dorrington, Theophilus, d. 1715.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[13], 191, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.H. for Brab. Aylmer ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [8]-[11] and p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:59728:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59728:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A <hi>Familiar Guide</hi> TO THE Right and Profitable Receiving OF THE LORD's SUPPER. Wherein alſo the Way and Method of our SALVATION is briefly and plainly Declar'd.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Theophilus Dorrington.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. H.</hi> for <hi>Brab. Aylmer,</hi> at the <hi>Three Pigeons,</hi> over-againſt the <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> in <hi>Cornhill,</hi> 1695.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:59728:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59728:2"/>
            <head>TO THE QUEEN'S MOST <hi>Excellent Majeſty.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe Your Majeſty</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>TO permit me, moſt Thankfully, to Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, That it is Your MAJESTIES very Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
<pb facs="tcp:59728:3"/> Approbation of Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Endeavour to revive the Decay'd Piety and Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the Age; which as it Animates me to proceed in that, and has almoſt brought it to Perfection, ſo it was the great Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement of this. In which I have endeavour'd to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade, and direct to the right uſe of this Bleſſed Sacrament; Which is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps
<pb facs="tcp:59728:3"/> the beſt and moſt Effectual means that our Lord has left in his Church to promote and maintain in it the Love of God and of our Neighbour. And may it pleaſe Your Sacred MAJESTY to give leave, That I may Encourage my ſelf from the Favour men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd, to Implore and Hope for the Honour of Your MAJESTIES Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage
<pb facs="tcp:59728:4"/> to this Small Piece alſo. I am, and deſire to be as long as I live,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your MAJESTIES Moſt Obedient and Dutifull Subject,</hi> Theophilus Dorrington.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:59728:4"/>
            <head>AN Advertiſement.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Have in this little Book diſtinctly ſtated and repreſented that So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Covenant with Almighty God, which we all of us enter into in our Baptiſm: Becauſe ſince the Recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of the Lord's Supper is deſign'd for a Renewal and Confirmation of that Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, the diſtinct Knowledge of that is neceſſary to our Fitneſs for this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; And I have further diſpers'd, through the whole, many weighty Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to Induce Men to keep cloſe to that Covenant; It being to us the Onely Way of Salvation: That ſo I might at once promote in many a Religious and Good Life; a Fitneſs for this Sacrament; and the Attainment of their Everlaſting Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:59728:5"/>
            <p> And having made this the Subject and Scope of this Book, I think it may not be amiſs to ſuggeſt, that it is very fit to be recommended and preſented by thoſe who have taken upon them the Charitable Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of being God-fathers or God-mothers, to ſuch as they have preſented to God at the Sacred Font. It is the Certain Duty of theſe Spiritual Parents, and the Charge laid upon them by the Church, to concern themſelves afterwards, and take all the Care they can, That the Child may be taught, as ſoon as it is able to learn, what a Solemn Vow, Promiſe, and Profeſſion, it has made by them. This Duty and Charge they would hereby, in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, perform; eſpecially if they would alſo concern themſelves after a time to know what <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe their Spiritual Children have made of it. Certainly if the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Charge of this moſt uſefull Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Relation were conſcientiouſly mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and in this and the like ways per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd; we ſhould not ſee ſo much deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Wickedneſs among Profeſſours of Chriſtianity as there is, and we might
<pb facs="tcp:59728:5"/> reaſonably hope to ſee the next Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, at furtheſt, deliver'd from the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Madneſs of this.</p>
            <p>And ſince this Covenant is implied in Baptiſm, when it is not expreſs'd in our Way: This Book will be uſefull to be read in all Families, in order to train up Young People in the Knowledge of their Engagements to God, and in the Way of their Salvation, and to a Fitneſs for this Bleſſed Sacrament, that they may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd in that Way. To Adapt it the better to ſuch an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe, I have added in the End a <hi>Prayer,</hi> which is proper to be uſed after the reading of any part of the Book in the Family or Cloſet.</p>
            <p>I think fit to recommend this Book alſo to the Societies of Religious Young Men in and about this City; That they may hereby at a cheap Rate, and with lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Labour, gain a right <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding and a diſtinct Knowledge of the Nature and Deſign of this Bleſſed Sacrament. To whom (as Young Perſons) this may be neceſſary and uſefull Advice; That they
<pb facs="tcp:59728:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:59728:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:59728:7"/> do not ſatisfie themſelves with Ardent and Devout Affections in their coming to the Sacrament, but endeavour to have their Judgments well informed too. For, as it will be of great Advantage to them towards a Holy and Good Life to have their Devotion built upon the Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a ſolid Knowledge; ſo, without this, the Adverſary of their Souls will have many Advantages againſt them. To whom, as the Glory of our Time, I moſt heartily wiſh that Grace, Mercy, and Peace, may be exceedingly multiplied from God the Father, and from our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:59728:7"/>
            <head>The CONTENTS of this Book.</head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 1. Introduction.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>p.</hi> 1</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 2. The Creation of Man.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>p.</hi> 5</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 3. The Firſt Covenant.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>p.</hi> 9</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 4. The Sacraments of That.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>p.</hi> 11</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 5. The Sin and Fall of Man.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>p.</hi> 14</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 6. The New Covenant.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>p.</hi> 17</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 7. On Our Part.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>p.</hi> 20</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 8. On God's Part.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>p.</hi> 31</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 9. The Sacraments of this Covenant.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>p.</hi> 37</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 10. The Lord's Supper, a Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>p.</hi> 42</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 11. An Earneſt Perſuaſive to the Lord's Supper.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>p.</hi> 51</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 12. Of Fitneſs to come to this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>p.</hi> 60</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 13. An Exerciſe of Thankfull Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of the Death of Jeſus Chriſt.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>p.</hi> 64</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:59728:8"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 14. <hi>An Exerciſe of Repentance.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>p.</hi> 89</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 15. An Exerciſe of Good Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>p.</hi> 100</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 16. An Exerciſe of Faitb.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>p.</hi> 111</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 17. An Exerciſe of Charity.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>p.</hi> 123</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 18. Prayers for Preparation.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>p.</hi> 139</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 19. Directions for a Devout Beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour at the Communion.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>p.</hi> 147</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 20. A Meditation on the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>p.</hi> 164</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 21. Prayers for a ſuitable Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>p.</hi> 179</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 22. A Prayer of Recollection.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>p.</hi> 183</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="guide">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:59728:8"/>
            <head>A <hi>Familiar Guide</hi> TO The Right and Profitable Receiving of the Lord's Supper.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECT. I. <hi>The Introduction.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THOU haſt here repreſented to thee, in a little room, I think, all that is neceſſary to render thee a meet and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable Receiver of the Holy and moſt Comfortable Sacrament of the Body and Blood of Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. And I ſuppoſe it is in ſuch a Manner repreſented, as is moſt fit and likely, with the Bleſſing of God, to poſſeſs
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:59728:9"/> thee with all the Qualifications requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite in him that comes to this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, if thou wilt afford this little Book a ſerious and frequent peruſal. If thou haſt been ſo unhappy, and ſo much miſtaken in thy true Intereſt, as never to have laid theſe things to Heart before, and to have liv'd in the neglect of this Bleſſed Ordinance; I would adviſe, I would entreat thee of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to read and ſtudy theſe things till thou art familiarly acquainted, and deeply affected with them; that thou mayeſt to thy Advantage come well prepar'd to this Sacrament. If the things herein contain'd have already affected thy Heart, and had a good In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence on thy Life, and thou art a fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Attendant upon this Sacrament, it may ſuffice to read this Book as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as thou canſt on the Week before thou comeſt to it, as a good Weeks preparation for it. And for thoſe who Communicate every Lord's Day (as I wiſh all Chriſtians did) it may ſuffice, commonly, to retire ſometime on the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:59728:9"/> Day before, or get up the ſooner on the Sacrament-Day, and ſeriouſly Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate on the Exerciſes herein propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, which are deſign'd to excite him that has an habitual fitneſs for this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament into an actual one, and are uſefull for that purpoſe. I ſay com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly this may be enough for ſuch; but yet even they alſo may find it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary and uſefull ſometimes, when leiſure allows, to read the whole.</p>
               <p>To make it as ſhort as I could, and yet as comprehenſive too, I have ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur'd to leave out what might have been ſaid to juſtifie the Method and Parts of it; preſuming alſo that this will not be neceſſary.</p>
               <p>Becauſe what is requiſite to render a Man a meet Receiver of this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is alſo neceſſary, and is ſufficient to conſtitute a good Chriſtian, and to bring him to Heaven: Therefore I have ſaid in the Title, that the whole Method and Way of our Salvation is herein plainly declar'd. So that if any Soul be ſolicitous about that Grand
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:59728:10"/> and moſt Concerning Queſtion, <hi>What muſt I do to be ſaved?</hi> he may find it herein reſolv'd. And whether this Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sacrament may be accounted and uſed as a Means of Converſion to a Good Life or not; yet I hope that, by the Bleſſing of God, this little Book may be ſuch a Means to many, if Men will but think it worth their while to do ſo much towards their own Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Happineſs, as to read and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider ſo ſmall a Treatiſe.</p>
               <p>That another Book ſhould be pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh'd on this Subject, after ſo many which have gone before it, will not ſeem ſtrange to any one who knows the Incomparable Pleaſure of Devout Thoughts, and the peculiar aptneſs of this Subject to afford them, together with the Inclination both of Grace and Nature to endeavour to poſſeſs others with what-ever has made a great Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion on our ſelves. And I believe, when this Book is well conſider'd, it may appear, after all the reſt, to have its Neceſſity and Uſefulneſs.</p>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:59728:10"/>
                  <head>The Prayer.</head>
                  <p>MAY the God of all Grace, Lover of Souls, to whom the Redemption and Salvation of Mankind is ſo very dear; and who invites us to this Sacrament as the way to Heaven, and that he may herein give us the happy fore-taſts of it: Bleſs this my weak Endeavour, and give it a ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs according to the Greatneſs of his Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Love; to the promoting in many Hearts the Love of this Sacrament, and their frequent and comfortable Attendance upon it; and to the bringing many Souls to happineſs and glory, for the ſake of Jeſus Chriſt our Mediatour and Advocate. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>SECT. II. <hi>The Creation of Man.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHEN it is ſaid in the firſt Chapter of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> that <hi>God ſaw every thing that He had made, and behold it was very good:</hi> This means, that the Creatour, upon the review of his Works, was pleaſed and delighted in them; and that He hated nothing
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:59728:11"/> that He had made: For, what we Hate, we wiſh that it were not, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially not ſuch as it is. If therefore the Creatour had hated any thing that He had made, He had made it to be ſuch as He would not have it to be; Which is not to be ſuppoſed of Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Wiſdom and Goodneſs, and of ſuch Power as is able to make every thing what He pleaſes it ſhall be. Mankind therefore, among the other Works of God, were made very good, and were pleaſing to our Maker. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed He made Man a very Noble and Excellent ſort of Creature, ſuch as muſt be peculiarly pleaſing to Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf above all things in this lower World: As we may judge by thoſe words in <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 27. <hi>God created Man in his Own Image.</hi> This was the pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Glory of Man, and that which chiefly advanced Him above the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures about Him: And it did princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally conſiſt in theſe things following. That as He had Faculties capable of knowing, loving and obeying God, He
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:59728:11"/> was diſpoſed to do ſo: He knew God to be the moſt Excellent Being, and did accordingly Reverence and Eſteem Him: He knew Him to be the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Good, and His chief Good, and did accordingly fix the choice of his Will upon Him; and valued His Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and Love, by which we enjoy God, as his greateſt and only Felicity. There was then no Errour nor falſe Reaſoning in his Underſtanding, no perverſe Choice in his Will, no Inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinacy in any of his Appetites, no Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in them contrary to His Reaſon. In nothing was Man enclin'd to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict his Duty to God, or any of the Eternal Laws of Righteouſneſs. Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this account it was that Man was very good, and belov'd of His Maker. And being ſo belov'd, He liv'd in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Peace and Happineſs: He was not encombred with any Evil; He wanted nothing that He had occaſion for. It appears His kind Creatour would not ceaſe doing for Him, till He had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for all His Neceſſities, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:59728:12"/> that ſo He might be compleatly Happy. Man then enjoy'd the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and ready Service of all the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures about Him. He enjoy'd Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and could with pleaſure conſider and praiſe God for the Noble and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Nature which his Maker had given Him: He had an eaſie and a quiet Mind, had no conflicts within himſelf, had no occaſion to rebuke or fall out with himſelf. He enjoy'd then his God too, being aſſur'd of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, and receiving the conſtant Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munications of it. He could, with great delight, contemplate and praiſe the glorious Attributes of God; And the Divine Wiſdom, Power, Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, Goodneſs and Truth were ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry pleaſant to Him, while he was aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd that all theſe were friendly, and would be favourable to Him. This was Man's firſt Condition; a very Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and Happy one; but, alas! through his own default it did not laſt long.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:59728:12"/>
               <head>SECT. III. <hi>The Firſt Covenant between God and Man.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT is very probable that all the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular dealings of God with Man, in this condition, are not told us in that ſhort account which <hi>Moſes</hi> gives us of the Beginnings of the World. It being enough for us to know in Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral what is the Spring and Source of all that Sin and Miſery which is now found among Mankind; The knowledge of which is of ſome Uſe and Importance towards our getting free from both. But what is told us of the Tranſactions between God and Man in that ſtate, we may think we ſhall moſt truly Underſtand, and moſt rightly Interpret, if we guide our ſelves herein by the Tenour of his dealing with Mankind ſince that. From what is told us, then, of that time, and from what appears ſince, we may learn, That
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:59728:13"/> it pleaſed the Creatour, when He had made Man, and had ſo highly oblig'd Him, to take upon himſelf the Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Governour to his Creature, as He had the undoubted Right of one; and he very juſtly thought fit to exerciſe a Dominion over him for his Good. It was therefore, we may ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, promiſed to Man, that He ſhould enjoy the Favour of his Maker, and a perfect Happineſs both of Body and Soul, upon the Condition that He would continue in the due Reverence and Love of his Maker, and Obey his Commands. And it was made known to him that He ſhould fall from the beſt of his Excellency, from that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in He was ſo pleaſing to His Maker; and from all his Happineſs, if he did not continue ſteadfaſt in his Duty, and perfectly perform it, as God had ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled him to do. And this is that which is commonly call'd <hi>the Firſt Covenant.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:59728:13"/>
               <head>SECT. IV. <hi>The Sacraments of That.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MOreover God having made Man to conſiſt of a Body and a Soul, and knowing that it is natural to Him, for the Objects of his Senſes to make great Impreſſions, and to have a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Influence upon his Mind: His Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Goodneſs order'd Matters ſo, as that his Senſes might help to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh him of his Duty, and to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure him of his Happineſs in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of it. And this we may ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe was the Reaſon and Ground of God's ſeparating two Trees, in the Garden where he had placed our Firſt Parents, for a peculiar and uncommon Uſe: The One call'd <hi>the Tree of the Knowledge of Good and Evil;</hi> the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther call'd <hi>the Tree of Life.</hi> Theſe we may reckon to have been the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Firſt Covenant: For in theſe were Spiritual things by God's
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:59728:14"/> appointment repreſented by outward and viſible Signs and Actions. Man was aſſiſted to remember his Duty<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and Obligations to his Maker by that Tree, call'd <hi>the Tree of the Knowledge of Good and Evil.</hi> For we may ſuppoſe that the Fruit of this Tree was ſet a-part by God wholly for the following pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: Man was to take care to culti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate this Tree as well as others; but he was to offer the Fruit of it at ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſolemnly and religiouſly to God, as a viſible Acknowledgment that he owned Him the Maker of all things, and the Supreme Lord and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietour of all. This was reſerved, as we may ſay, by God, to be a devoted Thing, and Man's Thank-offering to Him for all the reſt of his Gifts. And for this reaſon Man was forbid to eat of it himſelf. For we find in later Times, It was always held a very hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous and guilty Thing for Men to eat of, or uſe what God had ſeparated and reſerved to Himſelf. Now ſuch a ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, outward Performance, as the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:59728:14"/> offering of this Fruit to God, and the looking upon it and uſing it onely as a Devoted Thing, was an excellent and fit Means to admoniſh Mankind for ever to acknowledge their Maker and Preſerver as the Supreme Lord and Proprietour of all things: As it was a ſenſible Declaration that they did make this Acknowledgment, ſo it was a ſenſible Obligation of themſelves that they would continue to do ſo; and the more a help to them to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue it, and to anſwer all the Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which naturally reſult from it in the Courſe of their Lives.</p>
               <p>And then the other Tree was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to aſſure Man, upon his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Obedience, of his Immortality and Everlaſting Happineſs. So that whilſt he continued ſtedfaſt in his Duty, he had right to take and eat the Fruit of this Tree: And he might take it as God's viſible and ſenſible Pledge, and as an Inſtrument of Conveyance of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life and Happineſs to Him. In like manner, as now we have leave
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:59728:15"/> from God to look upon the Rain-bow, not only as the natural Effect of the Sun ſhining upon a falling ſhower, but, as God's viſible pledge and aſſurance to Mankind, that He will never again deſtroy the World with a Deluge of Water.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>SECT. V. <hi>The Sin and Fall of Man.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THIS account ſhows the exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing great Guilt and Wickedneſs of the Sin of our Firſt Parents. Their Sin was, that they did Eat of that For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden Fruit; and ſo they uſed and took to themſelves what was reſerv'd and devoted to God. It was the bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to a Common uſe that which was ſeparated by his appointment to a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious one, and was the profaning of a Hallow'd or Holy Thing. But let it be conſider'd a little how monſtrous and vile this Sin of our Firſt Parents
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:59728:15"/> was! How ſoon had they forgotten the mighty Obligations which the Creatour had ſo lately laid upon them! How bountifull had he been to them! How much had he freely given them! And He with-held and reſerv'd but one Fruit to Himſelf; and this, we may ſay, they grudg'd and envied Him: They would not be content with ſo vaſt a proviſion as he had made for them, but would needs have this af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded too. The poor depending Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that deriv'd his Being, and all he had, would needs be ſole Proprietour and abſolute Lord of all things on the Earth, and would acknowledge no Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour! They had no need of this Fruit, were perfectly happy without it; and might have continued ſo hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, if they would have abſtained from this; But they moſt unreaſonably de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed their Happineſs, and hazarded the loſing it for the ſake of the Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction and Advantage which they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected from this ſingle Fruit. The Creatour indeed had been ſo good to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:59728:16"/> them, they would not believe he would ſo ſeverely puniſh their Eating this Fruit, as he had threatned to do; and ſo that which ſhould have oblig'd them to be ſtedfaſt in their Duty, was moſt perverſely turn'd into an Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Sin. Oh vile and ſhamefull Wickedneſs! Let us conſider from what a vile Original we all ſpring, and be all humbled and aſham'd.</p>
               <p>In yielding to this foul Act, they loſt that Holineſs and Righteouſneſs which they had been endow'd with, and by which eſpecially they had been pleaſing to their Maker. In this alſo they broke the Condition of the Firſt Covenant, which requir'd that they ſhould conſtantly Reverence and Love their Creatour, and obey Him in all things. And the ſad Conſequence of this was, That they hereby loſt the Favour of God, and forfeited all their own Happineſs. They loſt all Right to the good things of this World; to the Obedience, and Serviceableneſs of the Creatures which God had made for
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:59728:16"/> them. They became liable to the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty which God had threatned to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict, and immediately upon the Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion did deſerve to have been put to Death, and to be thrown into the place of Everlaſting Puniſhment, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd for the Devil and his Angels.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>SECT. VI. <hi>The New Covenant.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AND the utmoſt ſeverity of the Threatning had been immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately executed in that manner upon them, we may believe, according as it was ſaid, <hi>In the day thou atteſt thereof, thou ſhalt ſurely die;</hi> If the Son of God had not become a Mediatour on their behalf. And He freely undertook to do what ever might be neceſſary to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it conſiſtent with the Honour of God to receive his Rebellious Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures into Favour again, to releaſe their Obligation to Everlaſting Puniſhment,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:59728:17"/> and reſtore them to perfect Happineſs. What He then undertook to do to this purpoſe, we may learn and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude from what He did in the Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Time: And that was; That He would unite Himſelf to the Humane Nature, and would become Man. In that Nature He would perform a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Obedience to God the Father, that He might merit, for Mankind, the Happineſs which was ſetled to be the Reward of perfect Obedience. And, to excuſe Man from the Eternal Death, which He had deſerved by his Sin, He undertook to ſuffer Death in his ſtead, and ſo to make his Death a Sacrifice for the Sins of Mankind. Thus much did He, very kindly and of his own accord, undertake to do for us; and he was accepted of the Father, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd that He ſhould, by doing thus, obtain the Favour for us which He de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſir'd. So He procur'd for Man that he ſhould not be utterly caſt off and thrown into endleſs Miſery; but have other terms of Favour appointed him:
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:59728:17"/> And this Diſpenſation or Appointment is that which is called the New Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant: And it is call'd the New Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant in his Blood, becauſe it was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur'd by his Undertaking to ſhed his Blood in the Humane Nature as a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice for Sin. Upon this our Firſt Parents were permitted to live, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy, in ſome meaſure, the Good things of this World for a while, and had ſpace allow'd them to make their Peace with God; to recover his Favour, and their own Happineſs.</p>
               <p>We muſt know, that ſince it was a ſetled Law before the Fall of Man, that He ſhould propagate ſuch as Himſelf; and his Poſterity ſhould be reckon'd in the ſame ſtate and relation towards God with their Father, who begat them: Therefore when the Firſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents of Mankind thus became pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by their Sin, and were fallen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſtate of guilty Rebels againſt God; All their Poſterity muſt needs come polluted into this World, as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean things out of unclean, and muſt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:59728:18"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:59728:18"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:59728:19"/> be <hi>born Children of Wrath,</hi> as the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſpeaks. We therefore have the ſame task upon us which our Firſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents had; that is, To recover the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of God and our Everlaſting Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, by performing now the Terms and Conditions of this Second Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</p>
               <p>Let us ſee then, what the Tenour of this New Covenant is: What are the Duties which it requires to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd on our part: And what are the Promiſes of it on God's part; the Bleſſings which it offers to make us partakers of upon the Condition of performing thoſe Duties.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>SECT. VII. <hi>On Our Part.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FIrſt let us take notice of our own part of this Covenant, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve what it is that God requires of us, to whom the Goſpel is preached,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:59728:19"/> which we muſt do to be ſaved. And becauſe all Mankind are now conſider'd by God as guilty and polluted Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; as having ſinned, and being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to do wickedly; There is firſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of us, That we repent and turn from Sin. In the next place, becauſe we muſt return to God; it is required, That we do believe all the Articles of the Chriſtian Faith: And laſtly, That we engage our ſelves, and endeavour to keep God's Holy Will and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, and walk in the ſame all the Days of our Life. But becauſe the Heart of Man is deceitfull and wicked, and we are ſo backward to do our Duty, that we are unwilling to know it; Therefore it will be requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to mention ſomewhat particularly, the Things contain'd under theſe three General Heads.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Firſt</hi> main Branch of our Duty is, That we repent and turn from Sin: To which purpoſe we muſt ſtand at a defiance with all the Cauſes of Sin, and reſolve they ſhall not govern us.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:59728:20"/> Therefore has the Church been wont to expreſs this Branch of our Duty thus: We muſt Renounce the Devil, and all his Works; the Pomp and Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of this wicked World, with all the covetous Deſires of the ſame: And all the ſinfull Deſires of the Fleſh, ſo as that we will not follow nor be led by them.</p>
               <p>We muſt Renounce the Devil, and all his Works. It was by the Craft and Inſtigation of this Apoſtate Spirit, the Enemy of our Happineſs, that Mankind were at firſt drawn into Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience againſt God. We muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve therefore never to have any Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence with him; to abhorr and abſtain from all thoſe guilty ways of conſulting him, or ſeeking his Aſſiſtance, which the ungodly World have ever practiſed. We muſt never, knowing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or willingly, obey any of his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, nor comply with his Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. We muſt reſolve to fight againſt all thoſe Spiritual Wickedneſſes in our ſelves which he infects the Humane
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:59728:20"/> Nature with; ſuch as Pride, Anger, Envy, Treachery, Lying, Malice and Cruelty. Muſt abhorr to imitate or follow him in the tempting of others to Wickedneſs; or in the Hatred and Perſecution of Good Men, for the ſake of their Goodneſs.</p>
               <p>We muſt alſo Renounce the Pomp and Vanities of this wicked World, and all covetous Deſires of the ſame: That is, We muſt reſolve and engage, that we will not let the Love of the World rule in our Hearts, which is oppoſite to the Love of God. We will not let our Hearts fix on the Wealth, the Pleaſures, or the Dignities and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours here below: Nor will make the getting of them the Aim and Scope of our chief Endeavour and Care; nor let the Enjoyment of them be our chiefeſt Delight and Satisfaction. That we will not be guided by the Cuſtoms of the World, nor follow a Multitude to do Evil: That our deareſt Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or our moſt neceſſary and moſt uſefull Friends and Benefactours ſhall
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:59728:21"/> not be able to Influence us againſt the Will of God and the Dictates of our Conſcience: That we will be ready to part with all that is dear, all that is neceſſary to us, and which we might otherwiſe lawfully keep and enjoy when they ſtand in Competition with our Love and Duty to God. And we will ſubmit to any Inconveniences in the want even of neceſſary things, rather than do any thing to gain them, which is contrary to the Laws of Divine Love.</p>
               <p>We muſt further renounce, mortifie, and abandon all ſinfull Deſires of the Fleſh: All the irregular and diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Inclinations of our corrupt Nature muſt be mortified and ſubdued. We muſt chace away thoſe fleſhly Luſts which war againſt the Soul; the Love of ſlothfull Eaſe and Idleneſs, all In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperance and Laſciviouſneſs. We muſt forſake and abſtain from all thoſe Senſual Sins, which abuſe and prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally waſte God's good Creatures; which enſlave the Thoughts and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:59728:21"/> of the Soul to the Appetites of the Body; and which render the Soul unfit for the due Exerciſes and Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of its Faculties; and which tend to clog and encumber the Body with Diſeaſes. We muſt renounce all theſe three Sources of Evil, the Devil, the World, and the Fleſh, and muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve we will not follow nor be led by them. And this is the Firſt main Branch of our Duty under the New Covenant.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Second</hi> is this: That we muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve all the Articles of the Chriſtian Faith. And this requires of us to promiſe and perform the Things fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing: That we will ſeriouſly apply our ſelves, as our leiſure and opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity will allow us, to make the beſt Improvement that we can of the Means of Divine Knowledge which the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of God affords us; that ſo we may gain as much of that ineſtimable Treaſure as we can: That we will not through Negligence or Hatred of the Truth be ignorant of any important revealed
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:59728:22"/> Truth: That what-ever does appear to us to be revealed from God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Himſelf and our Way to Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, we will receive it as certain truth: Becauſe it comes from Him, who is Infinite Wiſdom, and cannot be deceived; and is a God of Truth, and therefore cannot deceive.</p>
               <p>Theſe Articles of our Faith are ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marily comprehended in that <hi>Form of ſound Doctrine,</hi> which is commonly call'd the Apoſtle's Creed; among which theſe are chief ones. That we believe in God the Father, who hath made us and all the World. That we believe in God the Son, who hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed us and all Mankind; which implies theſe things: We muſt believe that all Mankind are guilty before God, and obnoxious to his Eternal Wrath and Puniſhment. That Jeſus Chriſt, the Son of God, died as a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice for the Sins of Men: That He ſubmitted to an accurſed Death as the Puniſhment of Sin in our ſtead, and to excuſe us from ſuffering it for ever:
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:59728:22"/> That his Death is accepted with the Father as an Attonement for Sin, and ſhall redound to the advantage of all thoſe who repent and believe on Him: Who being heartily ſorry for their Sins, and fallen out with them, do for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake them, and turn to God; and do expect and rely upon the Merit of his Death, to find favour with God. We muſt believe, that as Jeſus Chriſt died for our Sins, ſo He roſe again for our Juſtification: Having made a full At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonement, He was releaſed from the Bonds of Death; and is aſcended into Heaven; and that He ever lives there to make Interceſſion for us; that is, to obtain and beſtow upon wretched Mankind all the Bleſſed Benefits which his Death has purchaſed for them. And we muſt believe in God the Holy Ghoſt, who graciouſly applies all thoſe Bleſſings to us, and who ſanctifies us and all the Elect People of God.</p>
               <p>Further we alſo are bound and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to make our open profeſſion of the Religion contain'd in theſe Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles;
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:59728:23"/> and to own it to the World, that we are and will be the Worſhippers of the one onely true and living God, by one Mediatour between God and Man, the Man Chriſt Jeſus. And we muſt chuſe rather to ſuffer any loſs, or to die, than to renounce or deny our Faith. And we are bound alſo to lead a Life ſuitable to theſe Articles of Faith, to let them govern our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſations as they ought to do: And our Faith muſt work or operate in the Exerciſes of Love. This is the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond main Branch of our Duty under the New Covenant.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Third</hi> is this: That we muſt Engage and Endeavour to keep God's Holy Will and Commandments, and to walk in the ſame all the Days of our Life. And this obliges us to the Things following. That we will dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently ſtudy and learn the Will of God, as it is expreſs'd in the Laws which He has given us; will not cavil nor diſpute againſt our Duty, when we ſhould perform it; will endeavour to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:59728:23"/> know our Duty, that we may do it. That we will love his Law, and it ſhall be our conſtant Aim and Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to conform to it in all things: We abſolutely bind our ſelves, and are bound to live in no wilfull known and preſumptuous Sin. That we will not deliberately and knowingly treſpaſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any Law of God. This Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant indeed does not require of us to <hi>perform</hi> a perfect Obedience; for that is a thing now above our Power: But it binds us to <hi>endeavour</hi> a perfect Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience; that is, Not to be willingly guilty of any known Sin. There is, alas, no meer Man now that can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly and perfectly keep the whole Law of God, but <hi>in many Things we offend all.</hi> And 'tis one Bleſſing of the New Covenant, that it pardons Sins (as we ſhall ſee preſently) which ſuppoſes defects in our beſt Obedience. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore alſo our Saviour has taught us to pray as daily for the Pardon of Sin, as for our daily Bread. But this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant bears with none but involuntary
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:59728:24"/> Sins; ſuch as we commit through Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance or Surpriſe, and, for want of Conſideration, on a ſudden; when our Ignorance and Inconſideration are not wilfull, nor due to the neglect of our ſelves. And as for known, wilfull and preſumptuous Sins, and ſuch as are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberately committed; They put us out of this Covenant, and loſe us all right to the Favours and Bleſſings of it, till they are bitterly repented of, and ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly forſaken.</p>
               <p>Thus much we muſt heartily and ſincerely bind and engage our ſelves to do; and this is our part of the New Covenant. This is alſo called the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace or Favour; And we may ſee that it has juſtly that Name, in that it admits of Repentance for Sin, and accepts of that poor imperfect O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, which is all that we can now perform: And we ſhall ſee that Name further juſtified, in that it will appear to be one of the Bleſſings and Favours of it, that it affords us ſtrength to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form our Duty.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:59728:24"/>
               <head>SECT. VIII. <hi>On God's Part.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AND now I come to repreſent and ſhow what are the Favours and Bleſſings, or God's Part, of this New Covenant. What He offers, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, and will beſtow, upon our Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of the Duties and Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons required of us. And theſe may be comprehended under theſe Three rich and important Heads.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Firſt</hi> is a full and free Pardon of all our Sins. God will blot our Iniquities, as it were, out of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance; will forget that we were Sinners, and will treat us as Righteous: Will lay aſide his moſt juſt Wrath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us, and embrace us with Arms of Mercy and Love. He that might moſt Righteouſly have deſtroy'd us with an Everlaſting Deſtruction, will rejoice over us to do us good. He
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:59728:25"/> will pardon our moſt numerous Sins; will pardon the greateſt Offences; will pardon even our known, wilfull and deliberate Sins, and our cuſtoms of Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning upon our repentance and forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of them. And a general Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and a humble Behaviour towards God, will obtain the Pardon of thoſe Infirmities and Involuntary Sins which we do not obſerve our ſelves to be guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of, and cannot be perfectly free from. And having thus pardon'd our Sins, the Courſe of Mercy is free; all Obſtruction of it is remov'd, and we may addreſs to God with Boldneſs in the Name of Jeſus Chriſt, as to a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled Father; and believe Him rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to afford us all that is neceſſary to our Salvation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The next</hi> Favour and Bleſſing of this Covenant is, The reſtoring of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Image in us in our Sanctification. If upon the propoſal of this Covenant to us we do accept of it, and are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to yield to the Conditions it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires, and to give up our ſelves to a
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:59728:25"/> Life of Holineſs and Righteouſneſs according to the Laws of God: He will give us Spiritual ſtrength to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form our Duty ſo far, as that we ſhall be accepted through the Mediation of Jeſus Chriſt. If we will not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take, we ſhall not be able to perform; but if we will undertake, and bind our ſelves to do our Duty, He will inable us to perform it. It might ſeem a ſtrange thing that God ſhould require of us to bind our ſelves, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to do that which we cannot do of our ſelves, (as we do in obliging our ſelves to all thoſe things fore-men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned,) if it were not that the very binding our ſelves to this does entitle us by the Tenour of this Covenant to Grace ſufficient for us. In all the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortations of the Goſpel to any In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Duty, we may reckon there is comprehended alſo the Offer of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Aſſiſtance, which ſhall be afforded to. Him who yields, in the purpoſe, and deſire of his Soul, to comply with thoſe Exhortations. No Man there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:59728:26"/> ſhall have ground to complain, that he would leave his known Sins, and do the Duties which he knows he omits, but cannot do ſo: For if a Man ſincerely deſires to leave his Sins, devotes himſelf to his Duty, and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently uſes the Means that may inable him to do it: That is, If he waits on God for this Grace in earneſt and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevering Prayer, and a due attendance on the Preaching of the Word and the Sacraments, that Man ſhall infallibly come to be able to do what he thus wills and deſires. For, <hi>He that hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and thirſts after Righteouſneſs, ſhall be filled,</hi> as our Saviour ſays; And <hi>God, will give the Holy Spirit to them that ask Him.</hi> It is the Favour of this New Covenant to help us to do what it requires us to do.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The laſt</hi> Favour and Bleſſing of this Covenant, is an Everlaſting Happineſs both of Body and Soul in Heaven. We are left by it indeed ſubject to a natural Death; to mind us of our guilty Rebellion againſt God: That
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:59728:26"/> we may not forget we are Sinners, and do deſerve an Eternal Death: On pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that the ſence of this might quicken our deſire and concern to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the Divine Favour, and make us the more ready and willing to ſubmit to the Terms of recovering it. But Death ſhall not long have Dominion over us: God will not leave the Soul in Hell; that is, it ſhall not be always ſeparated from the Body; nor ſhall the Body be always ſubject to the Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominy and Puniſhment of its Diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Since the Sins are pardon'd which did deſerve Death, the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſhall be releaſed from it: And our Saviour's Reſurrection from the Dead does eſpecially aſſure the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of thoſe that believe on Him. He has alſo promiſed that he will <hi>give them Eternal life, and raiſe them up again at the laſt day.</hi> The Body, then, however ſcatter'd and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers'd, and loſt to all knowledge of Men, ſhall be gather'd together by the Wiſdom of God, and be raiſed to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:59728:27"/> Life by his Almighty Power: And it ſhall be raiſed with great advantage: <hi>It was ſown a Natural Body, it ſhall be raiſed a Spiritual Body; It was ſown in Corruption,</hi> but <hi>it ſhall be raiſed Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal.</hi> And the Soul ſhall be again united to it, never to be ſeparated more: But both ſhall be taken up to dwell in a glorious happy place, where is <hi>fulneſs of joy, and pleaſures for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more:</hi> To live in the Fellowſhip and Communion of kind, happy, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Angels: To dwell in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God, and contemplate, and praiſe, and love Him, and rejoice in his Love for ever.</p>
               <p>This is now the whole Tenour of the New Covenant, which was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur'd for us by the precious Blood of Jeſus Chriſt, our kind and powerfull Advocate.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:59728:27"/>
               <head>SECT. IX. <hi>The Sacraments of This Covenant.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AND this Covenant alſo hath its Sacraments. God has appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſenſible Actions and Signs in and by which it is to be made between Him and us. In the uſe of theſe Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments we muſt teſtifie our Conſent to this Covenant, and ſignifie, that we own our ſelves engag'd in it. And in the uſe of theſe muſt we wait for and expect the Bleſſings and Favours on God's part to be afforded us. It is by theſe that He has determin'd to convey thoſe Favours which we can at preſent receive; which are the Pardon of our Sins, and the Sanctification of our Natures; and alſo to aſſure that which we are to hope for, our Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Happineſs and Glory. Theſe we muſt neceſſarily uſe, then, if Means and Opportunity be afforded us to do
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:59728:28"/> ſo, that we may be partakers of his Favours: And in uſing them, we muſt ſincerely purpoſe and bind our ſelves to the performance of our Duty. The Sacraments appointed to be, as we may ſay, The Inſtruments of this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant ſince the coming of Chriſt, which are all that nearly concern us, are Baptiſm, and the Supper of the Lord. Theſe, and theſe only are now generally neceſſary to Salvation.</p>
               <p>By Baptiſm we are admitted into this Covenant, and make our firſt ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn acceptance of it. By the Lord's Supper we renew it, if it has been bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken on our part by any wilfull Sin com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted ſince we were Baptized: Or elſe we therein teſtifie and declare our continuance ſtill in it, and our purpoſe and deſire to do ſo; If any of us have liv'd ſo happily ſince we were Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, as never to violate or break this Covenant by any wilfull known Sin.</p>
               <p>It is true, when we are Baptized in our Infancy, we are not capable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsly to intend and deſign the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:59728:28"/> of our part in this Covenant; becauſe we cannot then underſtand or know it. But this Sacrament is in the purpoſe of God deſign'd for the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our admiſſion into this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, ſince the Appearance of Jeſus Chriſt in the World. And as that which was the Sacrament of this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion under the Jewiſh Diſpenſation was by God's appointment adminiſtred to Children at Eight days old; ſo the Chriſtian Church has been wont, even from the Apoſtles times, to adminiſter Baptiſm to Infants, from whence it is not to be doubted but they learnt to do this from the Apoſtles themſelves: And our Saviour gives a plain Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to the practice, when he ſays, <hi>Suffer little Children to come unto me, and forbid them not; for of ſuch is the Kingdom of God.</hi> Our Church there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as without doubt it ought to do, adminiſters Baptiſm to Infants, that they may partake of the Bleſſings of the New Covenant to their Salvation.</p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:59728:29"/>
               <p> But becauſe there is an engagement on the part of the Baptized perſon <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied</hi> in his receiving Baptiſm; the Wiſdom and Piety of the Church has thought fit that it ſhould be <hi>expreſs'd</hi> too: That ſo the Baptized perſon may be the better convinced afterwards, that he did thus engage himſelf at his Baptiſm. And becauſe the Infant it ſelf cannot expreſs this, the Church has provided, that ſome Chriſtian Friends ſhould do it for us, who are alſo Witneſſes that the thing is done: And they are bound to take care, that as we grow up to the Uſe of our Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, we may grow alſo in the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of our part in this Covenant, and may come to Underſtand what we are bound to.</p>
               <p>And that the Baptized perſon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf may ratifie and confirm his Baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Engagement, he muſt, when he can exerciſe his Reaſon, and know his part of this Covenant, readily chuſe and conſent to it, and ſolemnly renew it; And ſo he muſt make it his own
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:59728:29"/> Act and Deed to devote himſelf to God. This our Church has very juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ordered ſhould be ſolemnly and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly done in the receiving of Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation. A thing, alas, too much neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, to the great decay of true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Piety among us: But if this were duly and generally practiſed, we ſhould in all likelihood ſee more perſons live according to their Baptiſmal Vow, and as becomes Chriſtians, than commonly do.</p>
               <p>But this Diſcourſe is deſign'd chiefly to bring Men prepar'd to the Lord's Supper, that they may worthily and profitably Receive that; And therefore it muſt not be diverted ſo as to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt long on any other Subject but what is neceſſary and ſerviceable to that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign and end of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:59728:30"/>
               <head>SECT. X. <hi>The Lord's Supper a Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this Covenant.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Shall now therefore bring the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe more cloſe to this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, of the Lord's Supper, which has been all this while leading and aiming towards it. And I ſhall begin to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe particularly of that, by ſhowing, That it is appointed and deſign'd by God as a Faederal Rite, and is to be uſed as ſuch by us; As a Ceremony wherein this New Covenant between God and Man is renew'd and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd. This, by a little ſearch, we ſhall ſoon find to be very Evident in Holy Scripture.</p>
               <p>Our Saviour Himſelf, when He firſt inſtituted this Sacrament, ſpeaks thus of it, as He was delivering the Cup to his Diſciples, <hi>This Cup is the New Covenant in my Blood,</hi> Luke 22. 20. For what our Tranſlation renders <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament</hi>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:59728:30"/> there, had been more exactly and properly render'd <hi>Covenant.</hi> Our Saviour's plain meaning is this: Take this Cup as the Inſtrument of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyance to you of the Divine Bleſſings of the Covenant of Grace, which are the ineſtimable Purchaſes of my preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Blood. Again, when our Lord ſays of the Bread in this Sacrament, <hi>This is my Body which is given for you;</hi> and of the Cup, <hi>This is my Blood of the New Covenant which is ſhed for many for the Remiſſion of their Sins:</hi> He plainly means, That this Sacrament is intended to renew to us the Bleſſings and Favours, which are the Purchaſes of his meritorious Death, and his Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice which He offer'd to God in Dying for us. And the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> plainly teaches us to underſtand our Lord thus; For He ſays of the <hi>Bread</hi> in this Sacrament, It <hi>is the Communion of the Body of Chriſt;</hi> and of the <hi>Cup,</hi> It <hi>is the Communion of the Blood of Chriſt,</hi> 1 Cor. 10. 16. By Communion, he means the Communication of theſe.
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:59728:31"/> It is faithfully intended by God, that in the Uſe of this Sacrament, thoſe who are fit Receivers, ſhall partake of the Body and Blood of Chriſt; and this Bread and this Cup ſhall be the Communication of the Body and Blood of Chriſt to them: Theſe outward Elements of broken Bread, and Wine poured out, ſhall bring with them, to thoſe humble and prepar'd Souls which receive them, this Spiritual Grace: Which means they ſhall be partakers of the Benefits and Bleſſings purchaſed by the breaking or wounding of the Body, and the ſhedding of the Blood of our Saviour, the Bleſſings procur'd by the valuable Sacrifice of his Death; which are the Bleſſings of the New Covenant fore-mention'd.</p>
               <p>This Sacrament is Ordain'd of God to be a Pledge and Conveyance of theſe Bleſſings, and ſhall actually and infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libly be ſo to meet Receivers: God will never be wanting to his Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, nor leave them without the Efficacy He deſigns them for, if the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:59728:31"/> Receivers of them be not wanting to themſelves. He faithfully intends the Renewal and Confirmation of this Covenant with us in this Sacrament, and will actually do it if we ſincerely intend the ſame thing.</p>
               <p>And that the Renewal of our part of the Covenant at this Sacrament is expected and required by God, cannot chuſe but be very eaſily apprehended. When God offers good things upon Terms and Conditions, He requires the binding our ſelves to perform thoſe Conditions, if we would partake of thoſe Good Things; and our embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the Offers He makes, implies, and ought to imply, the accepting of thoſe Terms, and the engaging our ſelves to perform thoſe Conditions. To be ſure God never intends we ſhall be partakers of thoſe Good Things, without performing thoſe Conditions. When 'tis ſaid, God <hi>gives the Holy Spirit to them that ask him,</hi> 'tis implied that <hi>asking</hi> is the neceſſary Condition and Means of having; When 'tis ſaid,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:59728:32"/> 
                  <hi>God gave his only begotten Son, that they who believe in Him ſhould not pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, but have Everlaſting Life;</hi> 'Tis required that Men <hi>believe</hi> as a Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their obtaining Everlaſting Life. So when 'tis ſaid, <hi>Jeſus Chriſt is the Authour of Salvation to them that obey Him;</hi> and, <hi>Repent, that your Sins may be blotted out:</hi> Theſe things evidently imply, that our Sins ſhall not be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given, unleſs we <hi>repent</hi> of them; nor will the Bleſſed Jeſus Himſelf be a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour to us, if we do not <hi>devote our ſelves to his Service,</hi> and give up our ſelves to follow his Example and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct. Now this being the conſtant Tenour of the Goſpel; We muſt needs conclude, that when we are offer'd to be made partakers of theſe Bleſſings in this Sacrament, it is required, that if we deſire them, we muſt bind our ſelves to perform ſuch Conditions.</p>
               <p>Our receiving therefore of thoſe things which are God's Pledges and Conveyances of thoſe Bleſſings upon Conditions, is an outward profeſſion
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:59728:32"/> and declaration that we bind our ſelves to do what is required of us: And if that outward Profeſſion be not attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with an inward and ſincere Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it is a horrid Hypocriſie, and makes a Man undoubtedly <hi>guilty of the Body and Blood of Chriſt:</hi> He is reckon'd to have abuſed and profan'd the Body and Blood of Chriſt, as did the wretched Men that ſlew Him. The receiving theſe Elements in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament is an Outward Profeſſion and Declaration that we accept of God's Covenant, and then it certainly binds us ſincerely to intend our performance of the Conditions of it</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle plainly gives us this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10 in that he inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates the partaking of this Sacrament to be a Rite of the ſame Nature and Signification with the Eating of the Sacrifices which had been offer'd to any God. As the Eating of thoſe Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices therefore ſignified the Owning Him for God, to whom the Sacrifice had been made, and ſo the obliging of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:59728:33"/> themſelves to worſhip and obey Him; and the reliance upon that Sacrifice to find Favour and obtain a Bleſſing from Him; ſo the Eating of the Lord's Supper muſt be reckon'd to imply and declare the ſame Profeſſions and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements. This is the Eating of a Sacrifice made to God, even the great Sacrifice of the Body and Blood of Chriſt; and therefore muſt be attended with Faith or a reliance upon that Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to find favour with Him; the Owning Him to be God, and the binding our ſelves to Honour, Love and Obey Him. For this reaſon it is that the Apoſtle forbids in that Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thoſe who would partake of this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament the eating of any Feaſts upon Sacrifices which had been offer'd to the Heathen Idols; which Sacrifices he ſays were offer'd to Devils: <hi>Ye can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not drink the Cup of the Lord and the Cup of Devils; Ye cannot be partakers of the Lord's Table and of the Table of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils;</hi> ſays He, <hi>v.</hi> 21. <hi>Ye cannot,</hi> may mean <hi>'tis impoſſible</hi> you ſhould ſincerely
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:59728:33"/> intend what is ſignified by both theſe things; that is, the owning the true God as God, and the owning thoſe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils as Gods, for in owning one, you do imply the renouncing of the other. To be ſure the True God requires, if you own Him, that you do renounce all other. Or it muſt mean, <hi>You ought not</hi> to do thus. If you partake of the Cup and Table of the Lord, you muſt ſincerely intend thereby the owning of Him; and then you muſt not ſo much as ſeem to own thoſe filthy Devils in eating of the Sacrifices which have been offer'd to them: Therefore he adds in the 22d. Verſe, That in doing thus, they did <hi>provoke the Lord to jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie;</hi> becauſe they made a ſhow and appearance of departing from, and of renouncing of Him herein. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle then plainly teaches us, that in receiving this Sacrament, we do make a profeſſion and ſhow of Honouring and Covenanting with God; and therefore that we ought really and ſincerely to intend it.</p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:59728:34"/>
               <p> I might ſhow that the Name of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament</hi> was given to this Ordinance by the firſt Chriſtians, becauſe they reckon'd the Celebrating this Supper to ſignifie the Binding our ſelves to Serve and Honour, Love and Obey, and Truſt in God; to be His faithfull Subjects and Servants. And ſo noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious was it, that they uſed it as a Ceremony of Covenanting with God; that even the Heathens knew this, and therefore one of them ſpeaking of the Chriſtian Aſſemblies in his time for Worſhip (at which they always Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated this Sacrament) ſays; They met together on a fixed Day before it was light (this was for fear of their Enemies) and did there bind them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by an Oath or Sacrament not to commit any Thefts or Adulteries, not to betray any Truſt, or deal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfully with their Neighbour, and the like. They, then, took this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament as an Engagement to be of the Religion of Jeſus, and ſo to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the Terms and Conditions of the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:59728:34"/> New Covenant: We therefore muſt, when we receive it, ſincerely intend the Confirmation of that Covenant.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XI. <hi>An Earneſt Perſuaſive to come to the Lord's Supper.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Shall now inſiſt a little upon an Earneſt Perſuaſive to the frequent attendance upon this Sacrament, which the wofull and deplorable Neglect of theſe times, and the ſad Conſequences of that Neglect, do make but too ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary.</p>
               <p>Let all Men know then, that when they are come to years, and are capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to know and to renew their Vow and Covenant which they made in Baptiſm, they are Commanded by our Lord Jeſus Chriſt in this way to renew and confirm it. They are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpenſably bound to receive this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament in Confirmation of that Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:59728:35"/> No Man is left at liberty whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he will receive this Sacrament or not; but if the Providence of God affords him Means and Opportunity to do ſo, he is bound to prepare him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for, and receive it. If a Man at any time neglects to prepare himſelf for it, and is therefore unfit, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents himſelf becauſe he is unfit, in that Caſe he will be judg'd to have neglected the Sacrament it ſelf. He that does not endeavour to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd, and to receive it as often as Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity is afforded him to do it in that Congregation of Chriſtians, which the Order of the Church and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Governours of it does ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige him to join with; He does ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten neglect and refuſe it, as he thus abſents himſelf from it. But the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect and refuſal of this, we muſt know, is the neglect and refuſal of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable Bleſſings of the New Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant; of having the Pardon of our Sins renew'd and ſealed; the Bleſſed Influences of the Holy Spirit renew'd
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:59728:35"/> upon us; and our Title confirm'd to Everlaſting Bleſſedneſs, and our Hopes of it encreaſed and ſtrengthned; 'tis to neglect our own Intereſt, and to provoke the Diſpleaſure of God, more than by any other Sins, in neglecting the Offers of his Grace and Mercy.</p>
               <p>Let all thoſe who never mind this Sacrament, nor do ever prepare them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for it, nor receive it, know, That they do therein intimate the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing of their Covenant with God, and do cut themſelves off from all hopes and expectations of the Favours and Bleſſings of the Covenant of Grace, till they repent of this guilty Omiſſion of their Duty, and ſo come to this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament prepar'd for it. Oh wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Creatures, they chuſe to remain in a ſtate of Damnation. To be ſure a Man that has contradicted his Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, ſince he was Baptized, by living in any wilfull Sin; if that Man does not reſolve to forſake his Sin, and come to this Sacrament, and hereby bind himſelf to his Duty, he will be, in the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:59728:36"/> ſight of God, accounted to renounce his Chriſtianity, to deny the Lord that bought him, to trample upon the Blood of the Covenant; the Blood of Chriſt, and to deſpiſe his Dying Love: And as ſuch a Man muſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>evitably periſh, ſo he will fall under the heavieſt and the ſoreſt Perdition.</p>
               <p>What-ever pretended Wiſhes a Man may have to forſake his Sins, what-ever Regret and Remorſe for them, and what-ever Reſolutions he makes to forſake them, they will not be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted with God, nor bring him into a Title to the Favour of this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, if he has opportunity and means to partake of this Sacrament, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſes to do it: Becauſe 'tis <hi>in</hi> and <hi>by</hi> this Sacrament that God expects and requires the renewal of this Covenant after we have broken it: Our Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance is not compleated according to the Will of God till this is done, if he affords us means and opportunity to do this. We are not allow'd to expect that He will accept our Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:59728:36"/> and Vows in any other way preſented to Him, when He has ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed us this way of preſenting them.</p>
               <p>Beſides, Is it not a wonderfull thing that Men ſhould forget that this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament is appointed by God as the means to convey to them the ſtrength to perform their good Vows and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions? And then he that neglects this Sacrament, lays himſelf under the Power and Tyranny of his Sins, and neglects the mighty Help which Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven kindly affords Him againſt it: And He binds upon Himſelf the guilt of all his Sins, and as it were ſeals Himſelf to Damnation in refuſing and neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Ordinance, whereby He might be ſealed to the Day of Redemption.</p>
               <p>Let all Men know, that the wilfull neglect and refuſal of this Sacrament is a damnable Sin of Omiſſion, and puts every Man that is guilty of it out of a ſtate of Grace and Salvation: And they that neglect to come to this Ordinance, when 'tis prepar'd for them,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:59728:37"/> may very juſtly fear that God will not bleſs any other to them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For what ground have they to think he will bleſs one of his Ordinances to them, while they neglect another, or let them ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain by Prayer and Hearing the Word what he has Commanded them to uſe this Sacrament for, too, that they might obtain it; And then they that live in neglect of this, are in great danger ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to be ſaved by any other means of Salvation.</p>
               <p>Men may perhaps think themſelves very good if they keep their Church, attend the publick Prayers, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times hear, ſometimes ſleep away a Sermon: But if they neglect this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, they muſt expect God will reject all their other performances: <hi>He that breaks the Law in one point,</hi> the Scripture ſays, <hi>is guilty of all;</hi> And then he that neglects his Obedience to any one of God's Commands know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly and wilfully, will be lookt upon and treated by Almighty God as if he fulfill'd none of them. Oh that Men
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:59728:37"/> would ſeriouſly lay theſe things to Heart, and conſider the terrible Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger which they put themſelves into by this Neglect!</p>
               <p>Let us be aſſur'd, that what-ever it is that hinders us from preparing our ſelves, and coming to this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it is a Snare and Temptation of the Devil, the great Adverſary of our Souls: Who knows the great and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Efficacy of this Sacrament, and therefore would not have Men uſe it: Who knows, that if we ſeriouſly and frequently attend upon this Means of our Salvation, he muſt deſpair of ever accompliſhing our Deſtruction. Oh let us defeat the malicious deſign of our Enemy, and reſiſt all Suggeſtions that would beat us off from this prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice.</p>
               <p>Let us conſider how kindly and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vingly the Lord Jeſus, the great Lover of Souls, invites us to it: <hi>Come unto me,</hi> ſays he, <hi>all ye that are weary and heavy laden, and I will give you reſt.</hi> Let us not give him cauſe to complain
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:59728:38"/> of us, and ſay, <hi>Ye will not come unto me, that ye might have Life.</hi> Let us conſider what noble and inviting En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment he has provided for us at this Heavenly Feaſt: He deſigns to entertain us with aſſurances of his Love, with the Divine Influences of his Holy Spirit, with the joyfull pledges and fore-taſts of Heaven; and is this what is but fit to be deſpiſed! Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der at what a coſtly rate and price He has provided us this Entertainment! Even at the price of his own cruel Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, and bitter Death, and of his moſt precious Blood. If we love our Souls then, and have any concern for their Salvation, let us prepare our ſelves and come to this Sacrament as often as we can: If we have any true Love to the Lord Jeſus, our beſt Friend, our kind Saviour, who lov'd us and laid down his Life for us; Let us earneſtly deſire and ſeek the Purchaſes of his Blood, and ſeek to be made partakers of them in that way in which he has appointed us to do ſo; as we ſhall cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:59728:38"/> do, if we really and ſincerely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire them.</p>
               <p>I muſt not inſiſt too long upon this matter. If what I have ſaid cannot perſuade any unwilling Soul to prepare and come to this Sacrament; I would wiſh that I could but obtain ſo much of ſuch an one, as to read and conſider a ſhort Diſcourſe to this purpoſe, writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by His Grace the Archbiſhop of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury,</hi> call'd, <hi>A Perſuaſive to frequent Communion.</hi> There he ſhould ſee the moſt ſubtle Inſinuations which the Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary can ſuggeſt to with-hold him from his Intereſt and Duty, in this Caſe ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly baffled and confuted. And, as there is reaſon to believe that Diſcourſe has prevail'd upon many, ſo there is reaſon to expect both from that ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, and from the ſtrength of it, that none can conſider it well, but it muſt prevail with him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:59728:39"/>
               <head>SECT. XII. <hi>Of Fitneſs to come to this Sacrament.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BUT the common pretence and excuſe that hinders Men from coming to this Sacrament, is, That they are not fit for it: And they are afraid of Eating and Drinking unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily, and of incurring their own Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation thereby. It is therefore the deſign of this little Book to ſhow what Fitneſs is requiſite for a worthy and profitable Receiving of this Sacrament; and to help Men to that Fitneſs by the Bleſſing of God; which they ſhall not fail to obtain of Him by Earneſt Prayer, and the ſerious and frequent peruſal of what is here preſented.</p>
               <p>And ſince in Celebrating this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the Body and Blood of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, we are to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new and confirm this Covenant which we have been ſpeaking of between God
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:59728:39"/> and us; This will abundantly direct us what Preparation and Fitneſs is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite, that we may be meet Partakers of it to our profit and comfort. And it is neceſſary that we know what the Terms and Conditions of it are which God requires to be perform'd on our parts, and what it offers and promiſes on God's part. This matter there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore has been already for that reaſon diſtinctly and ſomewhat particularly repreſented.</p>
               <p>In the next place we muſt unfeign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly and ſincerely chuſe and lay hold on this Covenant; It muſt be the hearty deſire, the ſincere purpoſe of our Souls to be engag'd in it; To be bound in theſe happy Bonds which ſet our Souls at liberty from the Bonds of Sin and Death: We muſt deſire the Bleſſings, and ſeek the Favours of it, and readily accept and ſubmit to the Terms and Conditions; and declare, that we will expect our Salvation up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe Terms.</p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:59728:40"/>
               <p> And alſo we muſt, certainly, be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thankfull to the Son of God at this Memorial of his Death, ſince He be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came the Mediatour of this Covenant, and has by his Death procur'd the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of new Terms of Salvation, and the Offer of Peace and Reconcilement with God upon ſo gentle and eaſie terms.</p>
               <p>And he who has that Knowledge of this Covenant, and this good diſpoſition of Mind thereupon, that Man is fit for this Sacrament; and if he comes, he ſhall be a welcome Gueſt at the Lord's Table. Now as I have repreſented the Knowledge neceſſary to this, I ſhall go on to repreſent alſo more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly the good Diſpoſition of Mind which we ought to come with. And I ſhall repreſent this in ſuch a way, as will be fit to form it in Men where it is not; or to excite and actuate it, and ſet it into Exerciſe where it is. I ſhall repreſent it in the following Acts or Exerciſes of it: Which you may take notice are a lively Deſcription of a
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:59728:40"/> very meet Receiver of this Sacrament. So that he who would <hi>become fit</hi> for this Sacrament, muſt read and medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate on thoſe things, till he finds thoſe Diſpoſitions and Affections rais'd in him which are therein expreſs'd. And he that would <hi>know</hi> or <hi>find himſelf fit</hi> for this Sacrament, muſt examine him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf by them, and ſee whether they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent the ſtate and diſpoſition of his Mind or not: And if a Man be <hi>habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually</hi> poſſeſs'd with ſuch a good ſtate of Mind, as theſe things will be, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, very agreeable to him, ſo they will be of uſe to <hi>ſtir up that diſpoſition</hi> into Exerciſe, and to an <hi>actual Fitneſs</hi> for this Sacrament; As Fire is wont to kindle Fire in matter that is apt, and diſpoſed to receive it. Further, He that would <hi>behave himſelf rightly and duly at the Sacrament</hi> to his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and Benefit, as he muſt have his Mind then fill'd with ſuch Thoughts and Affections as are here repreſented, ſo the reading of theſe things there, if he has leiſure, will be uſefull to poſſeſs
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:59728:41"/> him with ſuch Thoughts and Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. And laſtly, <hi>He that would main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the good diſpoſition</hi> of Mind which he has at the Sacrament, may very profitably, for that purpoſe, read and meditate on theſe things afterwards: Which will be as uſefull to cheriſh and maintain, yea, and to improve in us this diſpoſition of Mind, as they are to form it. All this uſe, I dare pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, may be made of theſe Exerciſes following.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XIII. <hi>An Exerciſe of Thankfull Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of the Death of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>LOrd, I am not worthy to live, if I do not always remember the exceeding great Love of my Lord and only Saviour Jeſus Chriſt in dying for me; and if I do not moſt affectionate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:59728:41"/> conſider and obſerve the many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable Benefits, which by his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Blood ſhed, he hath obtain'd for Sinners. My Soul; That thou mayeſt know, in ſome meaſure, the wondrous heighth, the breadth, the depth, the length of the Love of God in Chriſt Jeſus: That thou mayeſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain the larger Apprehenſions of that Love, which exceeds all finite Knowledge; Thou muſt enlarge thy Thoughts, and take in all thou canſt of theſe Dimenſions of it. Conſider what a Depth of Wretchedneſs and Miſery Jeſus reſcues poor loſt Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind from! Conſider what a glorious Height of Honour and Happineſs he deſigns to advance them to! Conſider who the Excellent Perſon is that has done all this for us! Conſider what it coſt Him to procure for us ſuch a Redemption! Behold the moſt ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing, but the moſt pleaſing Proſpect in the World! Redeeming Love! Dwell in the Contemplation of this; for ſurely it is good to be here!</p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:59728:42"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>As for the Condition</hi> into which thou wert ſunk, It was the vileſt and the moſt miſerable that a Creature could fall into: It was perfectly miſerable, for thou hadſt utterly loſt the Favour of thy Maker, the Fountain-Good, and forfeited all Right, and loſt all Hopes of ever being Happy: Thou wert be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a vile Sinner, odious to the Pure and Holy God; and wert as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible as miſerable: Thou wert obnoxious to the Eternal Wrath and juſt Vengeance of the Almighty: Thou didſt deſerve to be thrown into the deep Lake of Fire and Brimſtone, where is Eternal Woe and Sorrow, Weeping and Gnaſhing of Teeth; where the Wrath of God burns for ever, and the Fire will never be quench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: from whence there ſhall be no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning. Where wretched Creatures are Furies to themſelves, and more than double all the Torments of Hell with this tormenting Thought, that they muſt all endure for ever: They will know no intermiſſion or reſpite;
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:59728:42"/> they will never come to an End. This is the ſad portion of Sinners; And this muſt all Mankind, after a few complaining days, ſpent in this low mortal Life, have been thrown into; And there was no Creature in Heaven or Earth could poſſibly have prevented this Doom; no, it could never have been avoided if Jeſus had not concern'd himſelf to help us. And he has taken away the neceſſity of our Deſtruction; has render'd this Woe and Miſery now an avoidable Thing! Is not this a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Benefit?</p>
               <p>Look down, my Soul, in ſerious Thoughts into that horrid Dungeon and Lake of Fire; Imagine, as thou mayeſt well, that many wretched Souls are already plung'd into it, who ſquan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd away the day of Life, the preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous time allow'd them of making their peace with God, and to avoid theſe Miſeries; Think thou ſeeſt them wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing in Flames, pierced through with Fire, and in all parts themſelves on a Flame! And be ſure, if thou could'ſt
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:59728:43"/> hear them, thou ſhould'ſt hear the moſt diſmal Howlings, bitter Complaints; ſome curſing the day that ever they were born, and all, at times, curſing themſelves as cauſes of their own ruine. And think now if one of theſe deſpair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Souls ſhould have an Angel ſent to it, that ſhould open the Priſon-doors and let him out, and ſend him into this World again to be in a condition and poſſibility of avoiding all this mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, would he not account this a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull Favour! Such as he could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver praiſe enough: Such as could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be worthily requited: It is, in truth, not leſs than this that thou art be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden to the Love of Jeſus for: It is not a leſs favour to be kept from this miſery, than to be deliver'd from it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſtate wherein now thou art.</p>
               <p>And thou art kept from this by the tender, compaſſionate, and moſt pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Love of Jeſus! Long ago, if thou hadſt ſuffer'd thy deſerts, thou hadſt been thrown into this miſery: Long ago have thy Sins deſerv'd it: It is of
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:59728:43"/> the Lord's Mercy that thou art not conſumed. Jeſus has repriev'd thee by His powerfull Interceſſion: He has procur'd that thou art hitherto ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; yea, he has procur'd that thou mayeſt, if thou wilt, be pardon'd; and mayeſt for ever be exempted from en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>during theſe intolerable Miſeries. Oh, how much art thou oblig'd! Say how uſefull, how neceſſary, how great is your Redeemer's Love! Oh, what Love, what Praiſe can reach it! Oh, compaſſionate Love, how ſhall I find Expreſſions ſuitable to thy kindneſs! Why was my Life ſo dear to thee! Why haſt thou not ſuffer'd me to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh! Me, who am as unworthy of thy Favour, as I am in diſtreſs, and the need of it!</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And does this</hi> engage thy Wonder ſo much, my Soul? It may indeed well do ſo; but this alone muſt not detain it: There are yet more Occaſions for thy admiration and praiſe in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer's Love! And this thou wilt ſee, if thou conſider what a glorious Height
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:59728:44"/> of Honour and Happineſs He deſigns to advance poor, vile, contemptible Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to. Thoſe that have render'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves unworthy of this Earth, and even of this low, mortal Life, he intends to advance them to Heaven, and give them an Eternal Life. Thoſe that are unworthy of any thing that is good and comfortable, He intends to make them perfectly Happy. Thoſe that deſerve the utmoſt contempt of their Maker; that are fallen under the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſults and Scorn of the abject Devils, He intends for the Honour of ſeeing God, and dwelling in His bliſsfull Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence for ever. Oh rich and bounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Love! Nothing leſs will ſerve him, but that where He is, we alſo ſhould be. Think, my Soul, if thou canſt, what Heaven is.</p>
               <p>Think of a bright and glorious Place, where this Sun would be aſhamed, and even diſappear, as now the Stars do at his riſing. Think of an innumerable Company of glorious Creatures, each of them more bright than He. Think
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:59728:44"/> thou ſeeſt them all in Joy, all raviſht and tranſported with Pleaſure, and thy ſelf among them partaking of that Joy and Pleaſure. Think thou wert now in the Preſence of the Fountain-Good, receiving immediately from Himſelf the Teſtimonies and Communications of Infinite Love! That thou wert there, where no Fear or Sorrow can ever come! Where the Joy is pure without allay! Where the Pleaſure is ſolid and abiding, not likely to leave thee in diſcontent and diſtaſt! Where the Joy and Pleaſure ſhall never End! Oh, how glad would'ſt thou be to find thy ſelf there! Thou mayeſt believe it is not poſſible for thy Heart now to conceive the mighty Joy, which would poſſeſs thee: And to this Happineſs, even to this, does the Redeemer's Love deſign to bring thee. He would have thee attain this Happineſs: He offers it thee on gentle terms: He offers to guide and help thee thither, if thou wilt but give up thy ſelf to his kind and gracious Conduct. And is not this ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing and obliging Love!</p>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:59728:45"/>
               <p> All the Joy and Happineſs of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven may be my Eternal Portion if I will; and ſhall be ſo if I am not want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to my ſelf. Jeſus has not been, nor will be wanting to do all that in Him lies to bring me to it. He does not grudge me the higheſt Bliſs that my Nature is capable to attain, or that my own kindeſt Wiſhes to my ſelf can deſire. He loves me, then, as much as I can love my ſelf, and is willing to make me as Happy as I can deſire to be; and more Happy than I can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive or imagine. Such is the Love of Jeſus to a Wretch that deſerves on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly his Hatred and Contempt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But doſt thou</hi> know, my Soul? Canſt thou think who the <hi>Perſon</hi> is that has done theſe great Things for thee? I am ſure, if thou hadſt not been told, thou could'ſt never have imagin'd it. Infinite Love indeed might be ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be in the Son of God; but He has Infinite Greatneſs, Majeſty and Glory too; He is exalted ſo far above us, that it were even Infinite Conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcenſion
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:59728:45"/> for him to regard or concern himſelf about the Miſery which ſuch low things as we had pull'd upon our ſelves. Beſides, He is infinitely pure and Holy too, and has an Eternal Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of all Sin and Wickedneſs; and we became miſerable by our Sin. And He loves the Father with an Infinite Love; and He made Mankind to Love, and Honour, and Praiſe the Father; but they have forſaken the End of their Being, and turn'd to Hate, and deſpiſe even the Good and Glorious God. And could it be imagin'd, that ever ſuch Perſons ſhould be Redeem'd, then, by the Son of God?</p>
               <p>But be aſtoniſht, Oh ye Heavens! Sing Praiſes, Oh ye glorious Hoſts of Angels! Produce your loftieſt Hymns, and help! Oh help poor feeble Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals to praiſe the Son of God! For it was He that became our Mediatour: He took upon Him the kind Office of being our Saviour: It was the Son of God that did us this kindneſs; The Eternal, the Onely-begotten Son of
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:59728:46"/> God; Who is the <hi>expreſs Image</hi> of the Father's <hi>Perſon,</hi> and <hi>the brightneſs of his Glory.</hi> This Perſon, my Soul, whom thou muſt own to be the true and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal God, by whom the Worlds were made; who ſuſtains all things; who is the Glory of Heaven, and the Stability of Earth; who is Incomprehenſible in his Greatneſs; and, to be ſure, Mighty to ſave, is He who regarded us in our vile Miſery, and moſt deſpicable Condition.</p>
               <p>Who pitied us in the Miſery which we had madly pull'd upon our ſelves which we had deeply deſerv'd! Who lov'd Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, the moſt hatefull things that are! Oh the wonder! that He ſhould retain Kindneſs, and think Thoughts of Love towards us after the abuſe of great Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating Love! To us who are altogether unprofitable to Him! Whoſe Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is not at all neceſſary, nor can make any addition to his! He had been Eternally happy if all we had been for ever loſt and miſerable, yet he would not ſee us loſt. He afforded his Help, when all other help utterly
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:59728:46"/> fail'd us, and we muſt have periſh'd, if He had not helped us.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But go on,</hi> my Soul, for the Way is ſtill pleaſant, and ſtrow'd with new and various Delights; and conſider too, in what Way and Method this Glorious Perſon the Son of God ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſht this great Salvation: What He undertook to do, and what to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, that He might ſave thee.</p>
               <p>Thou muſt know, then, that this Excellent Perſon meditated and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd no leſs Condeſcenſion, when He undertook to ſave thee, than to become Man for thy ſake. He intended it then, and in the fulneſs of time ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to it. <hi>The Word was made Fleſh.</hi> The Son of God took a Humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and became the Son of <hi>David:</hi> For he was born of a Virgin, who was of the Houſe and Family of <hi>David:</hi> A Royal Family indeed; but in this branch of it, at leaſt, ſunk into Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty and Contempt. He who made the Worlds, condeſcended to be made of a Woman! He who is Lord of
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:59728:47"/> Life and Glory, became ſubject to the Law that obliges Creatures! He whom the Angels account it their Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to attend and worſhip, made Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of no Reputation, took upon Him the form of a Servant, and expoſed Himſelf to the Contempt and Scorn of Men. Oh Son of God, how could'ſt thou endure to live upon this Earth ſo defil'd with Sin! To converſe with odious Sinners! We muſt needs won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that when thou wert in our guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty World, thou didſt not ſhow thy ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible Hatred and Reſentment of the Sins of Men in ſending Plagues and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolations about the Rebellious World. It is an amazement that thou ſhouldeſt here go about doing good! But this was thy conſtant practice: It was glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Love, Oh adorable Son of God, which brought thee down among us; and Love ſpake in every Word of thine; Love attended all thy ſteps; Love to Mankind was exerciſed in all thy Actions. What exceeding Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, Gracious Lord, haſt thou done
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:59728:47"/> our mean Nature, in taking it into a Perſonal Union with thy ſelf! Thus haſt thou exalted it above the Angels, and abundantly vindicated it from the contempt of Devils; Who firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fil'd, and then utterly deſpiſed it! So low and mean is thy Condeſcenſion, and ſo glorious our Exaltation! Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, my Soul, the Son of God become our Brother! And as He is our Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, He does exalt us to become Sons of God, together with Him; and his Father becomes our Father. Oh, <hi>what manner of Love is this, that we ſhould be called the Sons of God!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But this is not all the Condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Son of God to ſave Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind; That He took to Himſelf the Humane Nature: No; though this was much, yet He did more; much more than this. He undertook to die a Sacrifice for the Sins of Men, which, as God, he could not do; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore He became Man, that He might be capable of Dying: And in Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, He <hi>humbled Himſelf, and became</hi>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:59728:48"/> 
                  <hi>obedient unto Death, even the Death of the Croſs.</hi> And here, if ever, my Soul, thou wilt be loſt in Aſtoniſhment; In conſidering thy Saviour's Love to Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind: Thou wilt ſurely deſpiſe all things beſide: Thou wilt, like his Great Apoſtle and Lover, be forced to value no Knowledge but that <hi>of Chriſt and Him Crucified;</hi> and to <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count all things but droſs and dung,</hi> that thou mayeſt gain an Intereſt in this Love. That it may thus engage thee, conſider now the Death which Jeſus underwent for thee.</p>
               <p>Was it the Death of the Croſs? Was my Saviour crucified? And what a kind of Death was this? His Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, the Unbelieving Jews, choſe it for Him, and the Heatheniſh Roman Souldiers executed it. And this Death was the vileſt and the moſt ignomini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous one in the account of the <hi>Romans;</hi> ſuch as they put none to but the moſt contemptible Abjects, and the bafeſt Malefactours. And this Death was, in the account of the Jewiſh Law, an
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:59728:48"/> Accurſed one: He was reckon'd ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed of God that was <hi>hanged on a Tree.</hi> But let me conſider the Indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, the Contemptuous uſage which attended my Saviour's Death, and how painfull and afflicting it muſt needs have been to Him.</p>
               <p>As ſoon as the Bleſſed Jeſus was condemn'd to die, He was committed to rude Souldiers, who made it their ſport to injure and abuſe Him. They ſtript Him of his Cloaths, tied Him to a Pillar, and cruelly ſcourged Him on his naked Back. Oh Jeſu! I love and adore Thee, whom theſe Wretches thus vilely abuſed! I grieve for thy Injuries, and am afflicted with thy Pain! After this, they platted a Crown of Thorns, and forced it, to make it ſit faſt, upon his Head; wounding and tearing thereby his Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Temples; And then, my Soul, had I been there, I might have ſeen his own Blood running down, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſing his Bleſſed Face. Oh what a diſguiſe of that Majeſty and Meekneſs,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:59728:49"/> of that venerable ſweetneſs; that aw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Goodneſs which had always dwelt there! They then found out ſome contemptible purple Garment, and put it on Him, and put a Reed in his Hand to imitate a Scepter; and then mockt Him with bowing the Knee before Him, and crying, <hi>Hail King of the Jews.</hi> And, to ſhow how little Honour or Reverence they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Him in this, they moſt diſdain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſpit in his Face, and buffeted Him about among them from one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: And, without doubt, he thought himſelf the wittieſt of the Company, who could deviſe the greateſt Affront. Thus was He injur'd and abus'd, who came into this World on the kind de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of ſaving loſt Sinners: Thus was the King of Glory, the King, not of the Jews only, but of Heaven and Earth, mockt and deſpiſed, by the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt of Men.</p>
               <p>When they had tired themſelves with this Barbarous ſport, and how much rather Him? They put his own
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:59728:49"/> Cloaths on Him again, and led Him away to Crucifie Him. And on Him they laid the heavy and ignominious Burden of his Croſs, and he muſt car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, a long way, the Inſtrument of his Shame and Death to the place of Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution: But they had uſed him too ill before, to leave him ſtill able to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſo heavy a Load; and after He had hardly carried it a little way, He fell under it I ſee, O Son of God, in this thy fainting under the Croſs, a manifeſt proof that thou didſt really take our Nature upon Thee, with the innocent Infirmities of it: And I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not chuſe but admire and praiſe ſo wondrous a Condeſcenſion of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty for our ſakes. They who uſed Him ſo cruelly before, I muſt needs imagine, did not exerciſe any Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion to Him upon this occaſion. I abhorr to think how inhumanely 'tis probable they uſed Him now. But they laid at laſt the burden upon other. Shoulders; for now their Malice was in haſte to be rid of Him.</p>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:59728:50"/>
               <p> When He was come to the place of Crucifixion, they ſtript Him of all his Cloaths, and expoſed the freſh Wounds which the rude Scourge had given Him, to the cold Air. They laid Him upon his Croſs, and violently ſtretched out his Arms, and then drove a great Nail through each Hand: Thus faſtening to the Tranſverſe Beam of the Croſs, thoſe bleſſed Hands which had been uſed in the working many a kind Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle, but had never done any harm, and certainly deſerv'd a better Uſage. Then they drove one or two great Nails through his Feet, and faſtened them to the Upright Beam of the Croſs; Thoſe Feet which had carried Him di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently about upon his kind buſineſs in the World; which was to ſeek and to ſave loſt Sinners. This being done, they ſet the Croſs upright, that He might hang upon thoſe Nails, drove through thoſe very ſenſible parts of his Body, in exquiſite Pain and Torture, and expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to the view and ſcorn of the Spec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatours: And many of theſe revil'd,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:59728:50"/> inſulted over him, and derided him here. It would even wound a Heart that has any tenderneſs to think that any one ſhould be uſed ſo cruelly: And one could ſcarce forbear to feel ſome pity and trouble at ſeeing even the moſt odious Malefactour in ſuch a condition. But this was not a Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factour, my Soul, but as thy Sins had made Him one!</p>
               <p>This was the Innocent Jeſus, who had done no Iniquity, neither was guile found in his Mouth! This was thy Lover, thy Saviour, thy Friend that hung here; and all this he endur'd for thee. My Soul, if thou hadſt ſeen the Loving Jeſus thus hanging upon theſe Nails, and bleeding from his Head, and from his Hands, and from his Feet; and heard his Enemies reviling Him there, what Reſentments would'ſt thou have felt! Would not ſo ſad an Object have made thy Tears keep pace at leaſt with the drops of his moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Blood? Would it not have made thee alſo ſmite thy Breaſt as ſome of
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:59728:51"/> the Spectatours did? Could'ſt thou ſee this, and not feel thoſe Wounds, and ſympathize with thoſe Pains he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dur'd? When every Wound might be underſtood to ſay; Sinner, behold how I love thee! All this I endure for thee!</p>
               <p>How then ſhould this Sacrament affect thee, which is a lively Memorial of his Death! What a deep ſence of thy Saviour's Love and Sufferings ſhould this create in thee! When he is here as it were evidently ſet forth Crucified before thee! I ſee here his pale, wounded, bloodleſs, broken Body; I ſee his Blood poured out, and ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from it. Canſt thou ſee this, and ſay my Love is Crucified, and think thou ſeeſt Him crown'd with Thorns, all over daub'd with Dirt, and his Enemies filthy Spittle, and his own Blood, and not be fadly griev'd to think He was put to endure all this by His Love of thee. Oh, Crucified Jeſus, there was never Grief, there was never Love like thine! All this endur'd
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:59728:51"/> for me! This commands and deſerves; Oh let it cauſe my great Grief for, and my ardent Love to thee.</p>
               <p>But all this which afflicted his Body, was the leaſt part of the Sufferings He felt; He ſuffer'd more, abundantly more, than all this in the Sufferings of his Soul: For I muſt conſider further, that this Death of His was an Accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed one in the account of the Jewiſh Law; that is, in the account of God Himſelf; for it was He that had or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd and taught them to account it ſo; on purpoſe, that it might fore-tell and ſignifie before-hand, That the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer of the World ſhould bear in his Death the Curſe and Puniſhment which the Divine Law had juſtly threatned againſt the Sins of Men. This then muſt call to thy Mind the mighty Sufferings of His Soul, <hi>He was made a Curſe for us;</hi> and <hi>God laid on Him the Iniquities of us all.</hi> By Men was He treated as a Malefactour, and by God too. The Light of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Countenance, and the pleaſing
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:59728:52"/> Aſpects of his Love, which had been always the Joy of his Soul, and the Reward of all his Labours in his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and till now had been conſtantly enjoy'd, was now, when He wanted it moſt, withdrawn; when He was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der His ſharp outward Sufferings, and when He was at the point of Death. And in making his Soul an Offering for Sin, He was afficted and terrified with God's Almighty Wrath and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure. This made Him cry out, who was ſilent before, <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me?</hi> He felt the Wrath which our Sins had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved. Oh terrible thing! Who can conceive what He endur'd! We may believe no Torments can exceed thoſe He felt in his Soul, except it be thoſe of Hell, if they do.</p>
               <p>Oh wounding Thought! This ſtabs and pierces my Soul: This tells me, It was not ſo much the Cruel Jew or Barbarous Roman Souldier that tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, and kill'd the loving Jeſus, as the vile Sinner: It was I, among the
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:59728:52"/> reſt of Sinners, that gave Him his cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elleſt Wounds, his ſharpeſt Sorrows: It was I that wounded, that kill'd my Saviour and Friend: I ſhed his Life's moſt precious Blood. Was there ever ſuch a thing known beſides this? O Jeſu, there was never any Love like thine; and there is nothing ſo vile, ſo baſe as a Sinner! Greater Love than this hath no Man; that one lay down his Life for his Friend: But thou haſt laid down thine for Enemies, for thoſe that hated thee, yea for thoſe that kill'd thee: Thou art there on the Croſs deſpiſed, that I might be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour'd: Thou art there in pain, that I might be at eaſe: Thou art there hungry and thirſty, that I might be ſupplied with all good things: Thou art there accurſed, that I might be bleſt: Thou art there deſerted by the Father's Favour and Love, that I might enjoy the Everlaſting delights of it: Thou art there dying, that I might live an Everlaſting life in Joy, and Glory unſpeakable and Eternal. Oh Jeſu!
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:59728:53"/> Was I more dear to thee than thine own Life! Was I to be rather indulg'd than thine own Eaſe, and more to be reſpected than thine own Honour! What am I, Lord! Oh, what is Man that thou art thus mindfull of him! There was never Love like thine; None but a God could love thus! Oh Adorable Myſtery! Oh Wonder of Wonders! Thy Greatneſs is unſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, thy Love is incomprehenſible, and thy Ways are paſt finding out! With profoundeſt Reverence I Adore thy Incomprehenſible Love: I leave off to fathom what I can never reach, and will give up my ſelf to Praiſe, and Admire for ever.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:59728:53"/>
               <head>SECT. XIV. <hi>An Exerciſe of Repentance.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HAve I indeed given my kind and compaſſionate Saviour ſo much Grief by my Sins, and ſhall they give me none? <hi>Oh that my Head were Waters, and my Eyes a Fountain of Tears</hi> to drench my filthy polluted Soul! But, alas! it is not all the Tears that I am able to ſhed which could ever make me clean, or waſh out the ſtain of any, the leaſt of my Sins! Oh, I am become, it ſeems, ſo exceeding foul, and have contracted ſtains of ſuch a nature, that nothing but this preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſtream, my Saviour's life's Blood, can cleanſe me! How am I fallen from the Dignity and Honour of my Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion! I was made little lower than the Angels by my Bounteous Creatour; but I have made my ſelf more vile than the Beaſts that periſh. I was made ſubject to no Creature, not bound to
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:59728:54"/> pay any Homage or Service towards the Glorious Angels, though made lower than them; but, alas, I have made my ſelf a ſlave to the abject Devil. I have refuſed to ſerve God my Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker and Friend, and have drudg'd for my mortal Enemy. Oh wretched Man that I am! I have ſought his Service, while I have declin'd thine; and run after his Temptations, while I have endeavour'd to evade thy Commands. Oh, I have been forward to do Evil, and backward to all that is Good: I have combin'd with my Soul's great Enemy to haſten and encreaſe my Damnation.</p>
               <p>Infinite Goodneſs! How unjuſtly, how baſely art thou requited for all thy bounteous Love to Mankind! Who can conceive or expreſs the Vile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the Enormity of Sin! Which is a Contempt of thy infinite Majeſty, a Rebellion againſt thy unqueſtionable Authority, an Abuſe of thy free Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, a Defiance of thy Almighty Power, a Denial of thy incomparable
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:59728:54"/> Wiſdom, and an Affront to all thy glorious Attributes: Which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to that Honour and Homage which I owe thee as thy Creature. Wo is me that I ſhould ever offend my Maker! ſo liberal and ſo gracious a Father! Wo is me that I ſhould ſlight and affront the Love of Jeſus my Redeemer, as I have done it in cheriſhing thoſe vile Sins that He came to deſtroy! O Jeſu, at what a coſtly rate haſt thou lov'd me, and merited my Love! And how loth, how ſlow am I to entertain the Love of thee: Thou haſt Loved, where thy Hatred has been deſerv'd; and I, vile wretch, have hated Him that has infinitely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd my Love. Thy Love to me has been a vaſt Condeſcenſion, and has cauſed thy Humility and Abaſement; yet wouldeſt thou love the Unworthy: But my Love to thee would have been my Honour and Glory, my Everlaſting Advancement; yet have I been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to love thee. Wo is me, I have been obſtinate in Wickedneſs!
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:59728:55"/> Oh, how have I griev'd the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, in neglecting, reſiſting, and oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his good and kind Motions in my Soul; turning a deaf Ear to his gentle Admonitions, and refuſing to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted and healed. Oh my God, in our Sins we deſpiſe thy Will, and do our own! We diſown thee, and make Gods of our ſelves. In our Sins we believe the great Deceiver before the God of Truth: and follow his delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Temptations, rather than thy rich and faithfull Promiſes. In our Sins we preferr Earth before Heaven, the Creature before the Creatour; and reckon there is more Happineſs in the Enjoying ſome of them, than in the Enjoyment of Thee, the Infinite Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of Good.</p>
               <p>Oh how vile, how enormous a thing is Sin! Who can ſufficiently hate it! I ſee, O Lord, in the terrible Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of my Saviour, thy mighty Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure againſt the Sins of Men, and it terrifies me to think of it. I plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee how odious they are to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:59728:55"/> Purity; In that ſo worthy and great a Perſon, He who is ſo well and ſo juſtly belov'd of the Father, was ſorely afflicted by the Father Himſelf, when He bore the Sins of Mankind. I ſee thy Hatred, O Lord, againſt my Sins; I believe it very juſt, and I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not chuſe but hate them too. I will henceforth <hi>hate every falſe way, but thy Law will I love.</hi> I will love thy Righteouſneſs and Holineſs, and ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly abhorr what is ſo contrary to it, as my Sins. I will account it my great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Honour to conform to thee, and will abandon and be aſham'd to be found in the moſt creditable, or the moſt applauded Sins in the World. Henceforth will all Sin have a moſt deform'd and ugly Viſage to my Eye; I ſhall never think any one charming; I ſhall never account any one worthy to be deſired.</p>
               <p>But when I conſider, O Lord, the Courſe of my paſt Life; when I look into thy Commands, and compare with them my Thoughts, and Words,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:59728:56"/> and Actions, Oh what a mortifying View does this Examination preſent me! Oh wretched Creature, I am confounded, I am fill'd with Indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt my ſelf, when I ſee how much I have had to do with this vile, this odious thing! Wo is me, how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are my Tranſgreſſions! They are, alas, <hi>more in number than the Hairs of my Head, and my Heart</hi> even <hi>fails me</hi> when I review them. I have ſinned in every Age of my Life, ever ſince I could know or chuſe my Actions! Oh, wretched Creature, how early did I begin to ſin againſt thee! How many have been the unheeded Actions of my Life! the moſt of which, I muſt fear, have been wicked, ſince they have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from one ſo prone to do Evil as I. And how many more muſt the Sins of my Words in all likelihood have been, eſpecially while I did not ſet any watch upon my Tongue, nor keep the door of my Lips. And when I think how eaſily and abundantly the light Mind multiplies Thoughts, I tremble
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:59728:56"/> to think how much my vain, fooliſh, vicious Mind has multiplied Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions too. Lord, <hi>who can under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand his Errours!</hi> I am amazed at the Number of my Sins! I have ſinned, alas, againſt thee in every Circumſtance and Condition of my Life! I have ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in every Relation towards Men; Not doing that Honour, not paying that Juſtice, not exerciſing that Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to my Neighbour which I ought. I can view none of thy Commands, but it calls to mind many Sins I have been guilty of. Very often have I repeated the ſame Sins; <hi>returning</hi> to them, <hi>as the Dog to</hi> the filthineſs of <hi>his vomit;</hi> and, <hi>as the Swine wallowing in the mire.</hi> I have ſinned againſt thy Law, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Goſpel: Oh, how cold a reception have I given to the Offers of thy Grace and Mercy! How have I neglected the great Salvation! Tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled upon the Blood of the Covenant, and deſpiſed my Saviour's dying re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeming Love! Oh, how many of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men's Sins have I been guilty of!
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:59728:57"/> By my ill Example; by giving them needleſs and unjuſt Provocation; by tempting and alluring them to Sins; by aſſiſting what I ought to have hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred; by conniving where I ought to have beſtow'd reproofs; and by coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenancing and abetting what I ought to have corrected and diſcouraged. I cannot, alas, pretend to have done any good Action without a mixture of Evil in it: My beſt Works need the Blood of Chriſt to cleanſe them, and make them fit to be preſented unto thee: and indeed I want that Blood to waſh even the Tears of my Repentance. What a mighty Charge am I able to draw up againſt my ſelf! <hi>[Here thou mayeſt particularly mention thoſe Sins thou art ſenſible of.]</hi> But thou, O Lord, knoweſt me better than I do my ſelf; And I dread to think how much more thou canſt add to the heavieſt Charge that I can bring againſt my ſelf.</p>
               <p>I have been ſo vile as to ſin delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately againſt thee; to do Evil, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:59728:57"/> that I did Evil. I have been eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly induced to Sin; the ſlighteſt Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations have prevail'd with me! I have been, alas, accuſtomed to do Evil. O Lord, thou haſt Exerciſed wonderfull Patience and Forbearance towards me in a long train and courſe of Sinning; and I have been ſo baſe and ungratefull as to encourage my ſelf to tranſgreſs by that Patience which ſhould have led me to Repentance.</p>
               <p>Oh wretched and vile Creature that I am, I have greatly ſinned, I am be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come exceeding guilty! What ſhall I ſay unto thee, Oh thou preſerver of Men. I will lay my ſelf down in the Duſt before thee. I am at thy Mercy, O Lord, and muſt own that I have deſerved the utmoſt ſeverity of thy Wrath. In the ſad Sufferings of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus I ſee what my Sins have deſerved. I ſee in his Contempt how I have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd to be deſpiſed. I ſee in his Thirſt upon the Croſs how I have deſerved the want of all things comfortable. I ſee in his Agony, and by his Groans
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:59728:58"/> under the Divine Wrath, what Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure and Puniſhment I have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd to ſuffer. I ſee in his accurſed Death that I have deſerv'd to die, and be Eternally accurſed and caſt out of the Divine Favour. O Lord, I am unworthy, utterly unworthy to breath in this Air of thine, to inhabit this Earth; to enjoy this chearfull Light. I am leſs than the leaſt of all thy Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies. I muſt judge, I muſt condemn my ſelf, I muſt own thou wert Juſt, and I ſhould have but my deſerts, if I were now ſhut up in gloomy darkneſs; if I were now wrapt in Everlaſting Flames; if I were feeling the Torments of the never-dying Worm, and of Endleſs bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Deſpair.</p>
               <p>Lord, I will puniſh, I will take vengeance on my ſelf for my Sins. I will lead a Life of Mortification ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than Indulgence; I will never allow again any high or admiring Thoughts of my ſelf. It ſhall always keep me humble to think, how great diſparagement and vileneſs I have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted!
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:59728:58"/> to conſider my ſelf a Sinner, and that there is Imperfection and Sin mixed with the beſt of my Actions.</p>
               <p>But, O Lord, I beſeech thee do not thou enter into Judgment with thy Servant, for in thy ſight ſhall no Man living be juſtified. Oh deal not with me after my Sins, neither reward me after mine Iniquities. Bleſſed is the Man whoſe Iniquity is forgiven, whoſe Sin is covered. Spare me, good Lord; ſpare thy Creature whom thou haſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem'd with thy moſt precious Blood! Oh ſpare the miſerable Wretch that confeſſes his Faults; reſtore thou Him that is Penitent. Pity thou Him that is Contrite: Revive the Spirit of the Humble; chear the contrite Heart: <hi>A broken and a contrite Heart, O God, thou wilt not deſpiſe. Give me,</hi> then, <hi>the joy of thy Salvation; uphold me with thy free ſpirit: Then will I teach Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſours thy ways, and Sinners ſhall be converted unto thee. Open thou my Lips, O Lord, and my Mouth ſhall ſhew forth thy Praiſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:59728:59"/>
               <head>SECT. XV. <hi>An Exerciſe of good Reſolutions.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>OH Crucified Jeſus! Great Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr of Love! I cannot chuſe but acknowledge, and admire and praiſe the exceeding Greatneſs of thy dying Love! Much it is, O Lord, that I reckon my ſelf beholden to thee: And what, Oh what ſhall I render unto the Lord for all his Kindneſs and Benefits! Lord, when I ranſack my ſtore, I am aſham'd, I am utterly abaſht to find how poor it is. Oh, what can a Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture return to his Maker? What can I give, that have nothing to give; Who am nothing but what I have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riv'd from thee? Thy Goodneſs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is ſuch, that thou requireſt no more than we are able to render, and with that thou art well-pleaſed: But that, O Lord, is ſo little, that I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſatisfied with it. Oh let thy
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:59728:59"/> Fulneſs of all Excellent Grace, thy Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Love fill me with all true Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency and Love, that I may be the better and the worthier Gift to thee.</p>
               <p>Deareſt Jeſu! For the Love of thee I readily renounce all the flattering Vanities of this World, all the moſt neceſſary Enjoyments of it, that I may ſteadily Honour and Enjoy thee: I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count all things but Loſs and Dung, and will not count my Life dear, that I may finiſh my Courſe of Duty with joy, and may win Chriſt.</p>
               <p>But eſpecially, O Lord, for love of thee I do here utterly renounce, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate and abhorr all my moſt darling Sins. And it grieves me exceedingly that I ſhould ever be ſo baſe as to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain any Rivals of the Loving Jeſus in my Heart. O Lord, I hate them ſo much the more now, by how much the more I have formerly lov'd them. I will utterly caſt them out of my Heart; no more ſhall they harbour there; no longer will I entertain, no longer cheriſh thoſe thine Enemies.
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:59728:60"/> What! Can I be kind to the bloody Crucifiers of my Lord! See, my Soul; ſee theſe Murderers all daub'd with the Blood of thy Saviour. Away from me, ye hatefull Things: We will now inſtantly part, never, I hope, to meet again, never to be acquainted more. Begone without delay; I will thruſt you out of my Soul, you have no right to abide here. Jeſus alone has right to poſſeſs and rule me. Away vile Envy, I cannot endure the ſight of thee: Begone my Covetouſneſs: My Malice I hate thee: My Senſuality I will ſtarve thee: My Pride I will hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thee: My Idleneſs thou haſt made me ſo much work to do, that I am re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, I ſee it abſolutely neceſſary, to baniſh thee for ever from me. All my Luſts and vile Affections begone; ye ſhall have no more kind uſage here; do not expect it.</p>
               <p>Jeſus has all my Love, I have none for you. I am all his, I am no more for ye. Begone, ye hatefull Tyrants of my Soul. Jeſus, a kind and gracious
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:59728:60"/> Maſter, impoſes gentle Tasks, but you lay heavy Burdens upon me: His <hi>Yoke is eaſie, and his Burden light;</hi> but your Commands are rigorous and intolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Jeſus has ſhown me great and wondrous Love: Ye promiſe me much ſatisfaction and kindneſs, but perform nothing. No, ye have cheated and deceiv'd me: Ye have robb'd me of my Peace, robb'd me of my Dignity and Glory, and, which is more, ye have robb'd me of the Favour of my God. What can you do for me, if you ſhould do all that you promiſe, which is never to be expected, that is comparable with what He can do for me; what He is willing, and has faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully promiſed to do for me, if I will but hate and forſake you; or with what Jeſus has already done to teſtifie his God-will and Kindneſs to me. Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus made Himſelf of no reputation for my ſake, and that He might advance me to the higheſt Honour; But ye would expoſe me to the utmoſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of God, Angels and Devils:
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:59728:61"/> Jeſus has died for me that I might live for ever, but ye would kill me; Jeſus rules to ſave, but you to deſtroy. His Rewards are Eternal Life and Happineſs, but your Wages is Death and Miſery everlaſting<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> When I come to die, what fruit, what comfort can I expect from you? Alas, all that you could ever gain will leave me then, if it be not gone before, and I muſt go a poor, naked friendleſs Stranger into the Eternal World; yea, for your ſakes I muſt, if I do not caſt you off, appear a hated guilty Rebel before my Lord and Judge, and be expoſed to all the Terrours of Divine Wrath. But the Love of Jeſus will not then forſake me: Neither Tribulation, Diſtreſs, Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, nor Death it ſelf ſhall ever ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate me from the Love of Jeſus if I will but be divorced from you. And Jeſus is King of the other World, and will ſend his kind Angels to receive my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting Soul, out of the mean Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle of my Body, and to conduct it to a glorious Manſion: To welcome it
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:59728:61"/> from the Miſeries of this ſinfull World, to congratulate my happy Victory over you my Enemies, and carry me in Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph to a place of Bliſs, and to be with Chriſt. Can I then ſo much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon my Reaſon, ſo much miſtake my Intereſt, as to have any more to do with you?</p>
               <p>O Lord, the Great Redeemer have Mercy upon me, and deliver me from theſe tyrannous Maſters. Thy Service is perfect Freedom; in keeping thy Commands there is great Reward. Set my Soul, I pray, at liberty to run the Ways of thy Commandments. As for theſe thine Enemies and mine, bring them forth and let them be ſlain be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee: Root them perfectly out of my Heart. Let them from henceforth be in a decaying, languiſhing Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, never thrive more, and quickly die. I will never be ſatisfied till I ſee them utterly deprived of all Motion, Sence and Life. O Jeſu, thy Croſs, thy Nails, thy Spear are due to theſe: Let them from thence receive many mortal
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:59728:62"/> Wounds, that thou mayeſt never be diſpleaſed, nor I troubled or diſpara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with them any more for ever.</p>
               <p>O Crucified Love, thou haſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented me by thy Love, and infinitely exceeded all that I can return; But I will learn of thee to Love, and follow thee as well as I can. Thou haſt gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven thy ſelf for me on the Croſs, and giveſt thy ſelf to me in this Sacrament: Behold, O Lord, I offer my ſelf to thee, my whole ſelf. I offer and bring thee all the Faculties of my Soul, all the Members of my Body: I offer my Sences and my Paſſions: I offer all my Thoughts, my Words, and my Actions: I offer all my Deſigns and Endeavours: All the Labours of my worldly Calling; all the Adoration of my Worſhip and Devotions. I offer thee all my Poſſeſſions in the World; all the Perſons that I can command and influence to worſhip, honour and ſerve thee. I offer thee all the Days of my Life; I offer thee my Death when thou wilt pleaſe to require it;
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:59728:62"/> and both Living and Dying I deſire to be thine. I deſire to be entirely thine. Oh how dearly haſt thou bought this poor Gift! Never was ſo great a Price, beſide this, paid for any Creature. I will live to my Love that died for me. I will henceforth look upon my ſelf as a devoted conſecrated Thing, and will ever endeavour to remain ſo, and to carry my ſelf as ſuch. I will never be willingly employed, but as thou com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeſt, and as thou alloweſt. Lord, for thy ſake I will love thy Law, and it ſhall be my Meditation all the day. I will love thy Commandments above Gold, and all falſe ways I will utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly abhorr. Dearer ſhall thy Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments be to Me than Thouſands of Gold and Silver, and ſweeter than Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney from the Comb. I will love no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what thou loveſt, and will hate what-ever is diſpleaſing to thee.</p>
               <p>I am heartily griev'd, O Lord, that I have ever lov'd any thing but thee, while I neglected to love thee. I am heartily aſhamed to think that I ſhould
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:59728:63"/> place no Affection where all I could<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> offer is but due, and beſtow all where little or none was due Eſpecially does it vex and grieve me that I ſhould be ſo monſtrouſly ungratefull and miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, as to love any thing more than the loving Jeſus. Hereafter, deareſt Lord, I purpoſe to love nothing but far be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low thee, and for thy ſake what-ever I do love: And what is moſt like thee, or moſt ſerviceable to thy Honour and Glory, ſhall have the moſt of my Love.</p>
               <p>Henceforth it ſhall be my Honour that I am a Servant of Jeſus; It ſhall be my delight and pleaſure to be a lover of Jeſus; it ſhall be my moſt va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lued Wealth that He is mine, and I am His. <hi>Whom have I in Heaven but thee, O Lord, and there is none on Earth that I can deſire in compariſon to thee.</hi> And therefore nothing can be ſo ſweet to me; nothing can afford me ſo much ſatisfaction and joy, as to be able to ſay of thee, <hi>My Beloved is mine, and I am His</hi> For me to be thine, O Jeſu, is my Honour, my Security, my Peace
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:59728:63"/> and Happineſs everlaſting. For thee to be mine is health to my Soul, ſtrength to do thy Commandments; it is Joy unſpeakable and full of Glory; it is Heaven on Earth, and the Heaven of Heaven; it is Wiſdom, Righteouſneſs, Sanctification, and Redemption to me, O rich and bounteous Love. I am thine, O Lord, with all my Soul, that thou mayeſt be mine. Oh how much ſhall I gain by giving my ſelf to thee! I ſhall gain my ſelf and be ſaved from Everlaſting Perdition, and I ſhall gain Everlaſting Happineſs in the Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thee.</p>
               <p>I am thine, O Jeſu; ſave me, I have ſought thy Precepts. Lord ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie me wholly, that in Body, Soul and Spirit I may be thine: Take a full poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of me for the future; and let not any other Lords have Dominion over me. O Lord, <hi>I have ſworn, and I will perform it, that I will keep thy Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Judgments.</hi> I purpoſe to be <hi>ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt, unmovable, always abounding in the Work of the Lord, as knowing that my</hi>
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:59728:64"/> 
                  <hi>Labour ſhall not be in vain in the Lord.</hi> I am thine, diſpoſe of me as thou plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt: I will bear thy Yoke, I will not decline thy Croſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I will not deſpiſe thy ſhame: The reproach of Chriſt ſhall be to me greater Riches than the Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of this World. Let but thy Grace be ſufficient for me, and then call me to what thou pleaſeſt: I can do all things through Chriſt ſtrengthening me. Lord, I ſhall not, I hope, fear or decline to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer for thy ſake: No, though I ſhould die with thee, I purpoſe not to deny thee. But, alas, it troubles me to think how weak and vain all my Reſolutions are, and how ſoon they will come to nothing without thy continual ſupport and aſſiſtance. This troubles me; but it is my comfort, that thy Grace is ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily obtain'd; it may be now had for asking of it; O ſhield me by thy Grace againſt all Temptations: <hi>Hold up my go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in thy Word, that my footſteps ſlip not: Guide thou me by thy Counſel, till thou haſt brought me to thy Glory.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:59728:64"/>
               <head>SECT. XVI. <hi>An Exerciſe of Faith.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Believe there is onely one true and living God; who is the Father, the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt: An In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite, Eternal, Perfect Being; the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker and Preſerver, Owner and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of All things. Who has right to the Homage, Worſhip, and Obedience of Mankind: Who has laid upon us his Laws, and takes notice of our Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour; That his Eyes behold all the Dwellers upon Earth, and try the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Men; That He is always nigh to every one of us, for it is in Him that we live, move, and have our Being. I believe, O Lord, that thou <hi>art and art a Rewarder of thoſe that diligently ſeek thee:</hi> Thou haſt appointed a Day where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thou wilt Judge the World in Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, and render to every Man ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Works: That thoſe who are found wicked in that Day, ſhall go
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:59728:65"/> away into Everlaſting Puniſhment, but the Righteous into Life Eternal.</p>
               <p>But I believe alſo, that <hi>to the Lord our God belong Mercies and Forgiveneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, though we have rebelled againſt Him,</hi> if in the way of his appointment we ſeek his Pardoning-Mercy. Thou haſt, O Lord, Bleſſed be thy Name, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim'd thy ſelf a God, forgiving Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Tranſgreſſion and Sin: And decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, that thou deſireſt not the Death of a Sinner, but had rather that he ſhould turn from his Wickedneſs, and live. O wonderfull Condeſcenſion and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs! Oh how ſweet is thy Mercy! How glorious and great! The exceeding vile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and the unreaſonableneſs of our Sins, do magnifie thy Mercy beyond all Comprehenſion and Praiſe. Favour and Forgiveneſs to a baſe Sinner is that the Sinner could not expect till thou hadſt declar'd it ſhould be obtain'd, and didſt graciouſly offer it.</p>
               <p>When we were ſunk into the moſt abject Miſery by a vile Rebellion againſt thee; had render'd our ſelves obnoxious
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:59728:65"/> to thy Eternal Hatred and Wrath, and deſerv'd to follow the Apoſtate Angels in their Fate and Damnation, as we had follow'd them in Rebellion: Then did thy Infinite Wiſdom contrive how to ſhow us Favour in a way conſiſtent with thine own Honour: Thou didſt find out a way to ſpare Us, and to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh our Sins; to glorifie thy Juſtice in taking Vengeance on our Inventions, and thy Mercy in ſaving the wretched Sinners: And <hi>God ſo lov'd the World, that He gave his onely-begotten Son, that whoſoever believes in Him, ſhall not pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, but have Everlaſting Life.</hi> Thou gaveſt, O Father, thine Onely-begotten Son to the Condeſcenſion and Mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of taking our Nature upon Him; and to die a Sacrifice for our Sins; and on him, thy well-beloved Son, didſt thou lay the Iniquities of us all. And in his Death thou haſt receiv'd a full, perfect and ſufficient Sacrifice, Oblati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Satisfaction for the Sins of the whole World. Thou haſt laid our Help on one that is Mighty, and able to ſave
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:59728:66"/> to the uttermoſt all that come into God by Him. We adore thy Incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible Goodneſs and Compaſſion to Sinners! Thou art abundant, Oh God, in Goodneſs and Truth!</p>
               <p>Thy Mercy is over all thy Works: In Mercy thou haſt great delight: We remember the glorious Exerciſes of it; We know, O Lord, thou canſt pardon the greateſt Offences; For thou haſt pardon'd very great Sinners: <hi>David</hi> was forgiven his baſe Murder and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery; <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> his horrid Idolatry, and filling <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> with innocent Blood: The vile Adultereſs <hi>Mary Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalen;</hi> The Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> who denied and diſown'd thee with an Oath; The Furious <hi>Saul,</hi> who blaſphem'd thee himſelf; and being exceedingly mad a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee, compell'd others to Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme: All theſe are Monuments of thy glorious forgiving Mercy. Oh what comfortable, what joyfull Hopes have we in ſuch Goodneſs!</p>
               <p>We know, that having given us thy Son, thou wilt not deny us any thing
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:59728:66"/> that is neceſſary to our Salvation: But if we ask, we ſhall receive; if we ſeek, we ſhall find; if we knock, it ſhall be opened to us. On that Ranſome which my Saviour has paid for me, and on all thy gracious Promiſes which for his ſake thou haſt made, I do wholly and firmly rely. With an humble Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, O Lord, that we may find fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour with thee, we remember before thee in this Sacrament the bleeding Wounds of thy dear Son, and his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Death, our rich Sacrifice for Sin. We remember before thee, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent unto thee, Him whom thou haſt ſet forth to be a propitiation through Faith in his Blood. And in his Name, relying upon the Value and Acceptance of his Sacrifice, I thy poor unworthy Servant humbly preſent my ſelf before the Throne of thy Grace to ſeek thy Favour, begging leave that I may claim thy gracious Promiſes, which in Him are <hi>Yea,</hi> and in Him <hi>Amen;</hi> and that I may now entertain and delight my ſelf with the glorious Hopes which they afford.</p>
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:59728:67"/>
               <p> I deſire, I hope that thou wilt fully forgive my manifold and great Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions. I deſire, I hope thou wilt give me thy Holy Spirit, which thou haſt promiſed to give to them that ask Him. Oh grant me that Spirit to cleanſe me from all Unrighteouſneſs, to purifie my polluted Soul; to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all the filthy ſtains of my Sins; to ſtrengthen my weakneſs in Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; to be my ſupport and comfort me under Diſcouragements and Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; to aſſiſt me in all my Duties; to guide my Way, and ſecure my Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance to the End. Thou, O Lord<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who ſearcheſt the Hearts, and trieſt the Reins of Men, well knoweſt, I had almoſt ſaid too well, wherein my great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt weakneſs lies; Lord ſtrengthen me in particular, I beſeech thee, againſt mine own Iniquity. I deſire, I hope thou wilt graciouſly keep me unſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the World: keep me from following any of the Errours and Vices that ſhall ever be in vogue with the giddy and wicked Multitude. I deſire<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:59728:67"/> I hope thou wilt mercifully defend me againſt the Wiles and Devices of my Soul's great Adverſary the Devil. I humbly commit my ſelf to thy graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous keeping, Oh faithfull Creatour.</p>
               <p>I deſire, I hope, O Lord, that thou wilt bleſs me with Health, and with a competent Proviſion of what is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for me of the good things of this World; and defend me, if it pleaſe thee, from Poverty, Dependance and Contempt. Give me neither Poverty nor Riches, but feed me with Food convenient for me. I know, O Lord, Man is <hi>born to trouble as the ſparks fly upward;</hi> that Sin entring into this World, has brought Miſery and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction with it; And that our folly and perverſeneſs commonly needs ſuch Diſcipline to make us wiſe and good. I deſire to ſubmit to what-ever it ſhall pleaſe thee to order for me; to ſay al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways after the Example of my Saviour, <hi>Lord, not my Will, but thine be done.</hi> I hope thou wilt deal with me accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to thy Mercy, and lay upon me
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:59728:68"/> no more than thou wilt inable me to bear. I believe thou mayeſt do me great good by my Afflictions; I pray thee ſanctifie them all to the promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting my Soul's Health, and my Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Happineſs: And give me, I pray thee, an humble Reſignation, and an invincible Patience, that I may nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſpiſe the chaſtening of the Lord, nor faint when I am rebuked of Him: Let me always encourage my ſelf with this Aſſurance, That theſe light Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, which are but for a moment, if they be patiently born, ſhall <hi>work for<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> me a far more exceeding and an eternal weight of Glory.</hi> I deſire, I hope thou wilt direct and inable me ſo to paſs through things Temporal, as that I may not finally loſe the things Eternal. That by thy Conduct and Guidance I may at laſt arrive ſafely to that happy World where the Weary are at Reſt; where the Wicked ceaſe from Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling; where Sorrow and Sighing, and Pain and Vexation, and Fear and Care ſhall all be baniſh'd; all Tears ſhall be
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:59728:68"/> for ever wiped from our Eyes, and we ſhall enjoy thee, and all that we can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire in perfect Bliſs, and Eternal Safety and Quiet.</p>
               <p>This is a true Saying, and worthy of all Men to be received, That <hi>Jeſus Chriſt came into the World to ſave Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</hi> Lord I receive it; Lord I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, help thou my unbelief. I believe, O Jeſu, thou art Chriſt the Son of the living God, that ſhould come into the World. Oh tender and condeſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Love, how dear is that Bleſſed Name to me! Jeſus my Saviour! Oh how full of ſweetneſs is it, as a rich Perfume! Thy Name is as Ointment poured forth! Oh be thou ever <hi>Jeſus</hi> to me. To thee, O Lord, I fly as a refuge from the juſt Wrath of God I have deſerv'd; as able to conquer all my ſpiritual Enemies; as willing to receive into thy protection all that come unto thee. <hi>Oh Lamb of God, that takeſt away the Sins of the World,</hi> have Mercy upon my poor Soul; grant me thy Peace. Thou inviteſt thoſe that
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:59728:69"/> are weary and heavy laden to come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee: <hi>Behold, Lord, I come, let me find Reſt to my Soul.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I come to partake of the Happineſs of being united to thee in this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. I believe, O Lord, the Truth of all thy Promiſes, and the Vertue and Power of all thine Ordinances: And that the Bread we break, and the Cup we drink in this Sacrament, be not bare Signs, but real Inſtruments of Conveyance, and the Communications of thy Body and Blood: I come, then, that I may receive thy Body and Blood; may be intereſted in the Merits of thy Paſſion; that I may partake of the Spirit, and be intitled to the Heavenly Inheritance, which thou haſt purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for poor loſt Sinners. I come to make a Thankfull Remembrance of thy Death, which thou didſt kindly ſubmit to for the Advantage of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind: And by thy Death I hope to have Life everlaſting.</p>
               <p>I gladly embrace, O Lord, the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers of thy Goſpel. I deſire thee to
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:59728:69"/> ſubdue in me all my rebellious Luſts and vile Affections, and as a King to rule over me. I will account it my Honour to be thy meanneſt Subject. I deſire thee to afford me thy Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Inſtructions; teach me as a Prophet, and make me wiſe to my Salvation through Faith that is in thee. I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire thee to intercede for me as Prieſt in the Vertue of thy moſt valuable Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice; and to beſtow upon me the large Bleſſings which thou haſt pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed for Sinners. I believe, O Lord, thou haſt died for our Sins, and art ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen again for our Juſtification. I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire thy Death may utterly crucifie and till all my Sins; and that thy Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection may revive my Hopes. By thy Reſurrection I deſire, I hope for mine: By thy Aſcenſion into Heaven I deſire thee to draw my Heart and Affections from this vain empty World, to the hearty Love and earneſt Deſire of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Things: And I hope thou wilt raiſe me up at the Laſt Day, and bring me to be where thou art, and give me
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:59728:70"/> an Everlaſting Life. I take this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as a Pledge of thy Everlaſting Love; as the Evidence of great Love already ſhown me, and the Earneſt and Aſſurance of yet greater Communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to come.</p>
               <p>My Soul thirſts for God, even for the Living God: Oh, when ſhall I come and appear before God! When ſhall I ſee thy Face, O deareſt Jeſu, without a Veil, be kiſs'd with the Kiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of thy Mouth, enjoy thy ſelf im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately? When ſhall theſe ſhort and faint Glimpſes of thy Glory be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chang'd for a full abiding ſight of thee? When ſhall I have leave not onely to viſit, but to dwell with thee; and to receive not tranſient Taſts, but drink large Draughts of Delight and Joy from an Infinite Fountain of Bliſs and Joy: For in thy <hi>preſence is fulneſs of joy, and at thy right hand are pleaſures for evermore.</hi> Oh how I long that this my weary Pilgrimage were done: That I were abſent from the Body, that I might be preſent with the Lord:
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:59728:70"/> That I might have no neceſſary diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, deareſt Jeſu, from perpetual con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templating, praiſing, loving and enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thee. For this however I do wait; This I do through thy Merits, and from thy Infinite Love expect; and that Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation ſhall encourage me to labour in thy Service, to bear thy Croſs, and to follow thee whitherſoever thou ſhalt call me.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XVII. <hi>An Exerciſe of Charity.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>O Jeſu, thou art Infinite Love! I cannot but with great delight and wonder Contemplate thee; and when I do ſo, I feel a pleaſing Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint upon me to Love. I muſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count this a moſt excellent and divine Qualification, which is ſo eminently in thee: I muſt reckon it my greateſt Honour to be conform'd to the Son of God; and therefore I muſt utterly
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:59728:71"/> diſlike and hate my ſelf for any defect of Love I find in my ſelf. Beſides<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> When I think how much I am lov'd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> How much thy free and bounteous Love has given, and how much it has forgiven to me, I am forced to account my ſelf baſely and extreamly unworthy of this if I do not love much.</p>
               <p>I will put on, then, the moſt exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Charity that I can: I will wiſh well, and do good to all Men as far as I have power, and as oft as I have op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to do it: I will love my Neighbour as my ſelf; and account him my Neighbour, who has any need of my kindneſs, and to whom I have it in my power to do any Office of kindneſs, whoſoever he be. Thou, O Bleſſed Jeſu, haſt lov'd the moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy Wretches! I, then, will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count none unworthy of my Love and Good-will. Thou haſt lov'd thoſe that were infinitely below thee, and haſt mightily condeſcended to do them kindneſs. I will never account it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low me therefore to do an Office of
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:59728:71"/> Kindneſs to my meaneſt Neighbour; but rather the greater the Condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is in the doing it, the more I will value the opportunity, of ſhowing therein the greater Likeneſs and Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude to thee. Thou, Lord, haſt lov'd thoſe that are altogether unprofitable to thee; and from whom thou canſt never receive a parallel return of Love: I will be aſham'd, then, as I moſt juſtly may, to beſtow no Benefits but where I have receiv'd, or expect to receive ſome.</p>
               <p>Thou, O Jeſu, haſt lov'd even thine Enemies, and pray'd for thoſe that <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpitefully uſed and perſecuted thee:</hi> And this is a glorious Pattern which I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, by the Aſſiſtance of thy Grace, to imitate. As for all that have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jur'd me by Word or Deed, O Lord, I forgive them, and I pray thee to forgive them. I am more ſorry for their Errour and Sin, than I am for any Loſs and Damage which is come, or may come to me by their Injury: Lord have Mercy upon their Souls;
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:59728:72"/> Forgive my Enemies, Perſecutours and Slanderers, and turn their Hearts. I deſire no harm to any that are my Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, if any be ſo: Nor will I rejoice over them when they fall, but rather grieve to ſee it; much leſs will I ever ſeek their harm and miſchief. And I purpoſe on the contrary, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all their unkindneſs, to do them all the good Offices which I can; conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtently with a due care of my own ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and with other Obligations and Duties to thee, or to others of my Neighbours. I purpoſe to ſtudy, and ſeek to do them good: To return Bleſſing for Curſing, Reſpect for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, and Good for Evil: That I may, if it be poſſible, <hi>overcome Evil with Good.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As it is the Character of Charity not to be forward to think Evil, I will take care that no uncharitable Jealouſies or Suſpicions of my Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour may repreſent him my Enemy who is not ſo: I will take care not to interpret a miſtake into a malicious
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:59728:72"/> deſign; or that which is intended as a kindneſs, into an injury: But will always endeavour to take all his Words and Actions in the beſt Sence, and to put the beſt Interpretation upon them all that I can: Eſpecially will I do thus by the Magiſtrate, as being bound to it by the Obligation to Reverence, and Honour him as well as by the Laws of Charity; and becauſe it is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and uſefull to the Publick Peace and Welfare, and ſo is in its Effects a Charity to others of my Neighbours too.</p>
               <p>I thank thee, O Lord, for all the kindneſs of my Friends, and for thoſe that have done me any good: I pray thee, O bounteous Love, abundantly to requite them in this World and the next; in Temporal and Eternal. Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings Continue or encreaſe their Store and Worldly Proſperity, if it may be good for them; and eſpecially Bleſs them with Spiritual Bleſſings in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Things. I will endeavour, as far as lies in my power, in what I can
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:59728:73"/> do for their outward Eſtate, or for their Souls, always to expreſs a moſt gratefull Sence of their kindneſs. I will not deſpiſe the Love of the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt perſon, much rather will I thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully reſent the condeſcending Favours of thoſe that are above me.</p>
               <p>I make my humble Supplications to thee now, O Lord, at a good time, for all Mankind: I recommend to thy Infinite Mercy all <hi>Jews, Turks</hi> and <hi>Infidels.</hi> Oh let them that ſit in Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſee thy marvellous Light, and be turned from the Power of Satan unto God: That the Earth might be filled with Knowledge of the Lord as Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters cover the Sea. Let thy Goſpel of Holineſs, Peace and Love, O Jeſu, run and be glorified from the riſing of the Sun, to the going down of the ſame.</p>
               <p>With great Trouble and Concern, O Lord, I conſider how much of the wretched World lies in Wickedneſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> O how ſad a Thought is it, that ſuch a Saviour ſhould be offer'd to Men, and ſo few receive Him! How ſad is it to
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:59728:73"/> think that ſo many Thouſands of Souls for whom Chriſt died, are likely to go down into the diſmal Caves of Hell; that ſo many who might be Eternally happy, and praiſe thee for ever, will deſtroy, and throw themſelves into E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Miſery. <hi>Rivers of Waters run down mine Eyes, becauſe Men make void thy Law:</hi> A Law ſo rich in Love, and ſo condeſcending in Grace. I am troubled, O Lord, becauſe they do not love thee, and becauſe they will deſtroy themſelves: Becauſe they af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front and rebell againſt thy moſt obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Goodneſs, and neglect ſo great Salvation as it offers them.</p>
               <p>Oh that I could ſave many precious Souls from their Deſtruction; Oh that I could pluck them as Brands out of the Burning. As far as I am able, and as becomes me to do in my place and ſtation, I will endeavour to cure the Epidemical Wickedneſs of the Times I live in. I will earneſtly endeavour to keep thoſe Souls that are under my Authority and Power, and that are of
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:59728:74"/> my Neighbourhood and Acquaintance, and whom I can have any influence over from going down to Everlaſting Perdition. I will follow all that I may with Advice and Counſel; and thoſe that I may not pretend to adviſe, I will endeavour to entreat, that they would be ſaved: And thoſe whom I ought to do this to, I will reprove and correct for any Wickedneſs that I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve in them. I will propagate, as well as I can, the ſaving Knowledge, and the Love of thee among the Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and Careleſs, and thoſe whom their Poverty hinders from providing for themſelves; By giving among them, according to my Ability, ſuch means of their Inſtruction and Reformation as thy Favour has afforded the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick.</p>
               <p>I am greatly troubled and concern'd at the Miſeries and Calamities which I hear of or ſee in the World: That thy Creatures whom thou didſt make, that thou mighteſt love them, and that they might be happy, ſhould pull upon
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:59728:74"/> themſelves ſo much Miſery from thy juſt Wrath, and deſerved Vengeance. Oh how ſad is it to think of Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of People going down alive into the Pit, ſwallow'd up by ſudden Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes; and in a moment ſnatch'd hence into Eternity, without any time to prepare for their Departure. How it grieves me to think of the ſad Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of Pining Famine in ſome places; of Infectious and Peſtilential Diſeaſes in others. It wounds my Soul to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the wofull Calamities and Deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations that attend Horrid Wars<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Oh how deplorable a thing is it that Men ſhould ſeek to ſpill the Blood of Men; and give the Carkaſſes of their own Kind for a Prey to Birds and Wild Beaſts. Lord, rebuke the proud Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbers of the World; abate their Pride, aſſwage their Malice, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found their Devices: Grant that Wars may ceaſe in all Lands, and gentle Love and happy Peace abound! Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper, good Lord, thoſe that Endeavour for a juſt and ſafe Peace, that they
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:59728:75"/> may attain it; and <hi>ſcatter thou the People that delight in War.</hi> Oh that thy Judgments which are abroad in Earth, might make the Inhabitants of the World to learn Righteouſneſs, and turn themſelves to thee who haſt ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten them, that thou mayeſt head them.</p>
               <p>As a Member of thy Bleſſed Church, I am particularly concern'd for the Tranquillity and Peace, and the true Spiritual Glory and Proſperity of that. O Lord, purge out of thy Church what-ever does diſpleaſe thee, and is deſtructive to the Souls of Men. Purge out of it what-ever is an Offence to thoſe without: Poſſeſs all Chriſtians with this, That they are oblig'd to En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour, that their Carriage may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorn and recommend their Religion in the ſight of the Infidels; and to take care their <hi>Light may ſo ſhine before Men, that they ſeeing their Good Works<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> may Glorifie their Father which is in Heaven.</hi> Purge thy Church, we pray thee, from all falſe Doctrines and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies;
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:59728:75"/> from Prophaneneſs and Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution; from Superſtition and Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; from Envy, Hatred, Malice, and all Uncharitableneſs. Bring into the Way of Truth all ſuch as have erred, and are deceived: Raiſe up them that are fallen; confirm, and ſtrengthen thoſe that ſtand in Piety and Vertue, and Profeſſion of the Truth. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort thoſe parts of thy Church that mourn, and are oppreſs'd under a Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous Perſecution; And let thine own Right-hand, and Holy Arm, in thy due time, give them a mighty Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>O God of Love, O Prince of Peace, and God of Order, we pray thee let thy Goſpel abundantly promote theſe good things in thy Church. Grant that there may be <hi>no hurting nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying in all thy Holy Mountain:</hi> That all the Members of the Church, as Members of the ſame Body, and of one another, may have a Cordial Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to each other: Carrying them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with <hi>all lowlineſs and meekneſs</hi> to
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:59728:76"/> each other; and with <hi>long-ſuffering, forbearing one another in Love.</hi> Grant that as there is but <hi>one Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> whom we all pretend to Love and Reverence, as there is but <hi>one</hi> true <hi>Faith, one Baptiſm, one God and Father of us all,</hi> ſo we may all <hi>with one Mind and one Mouth glorifie thee our God.</hi> Grant that every Member of the Church may ſo know and keep its pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per place, that there may be <hi>no Schiſm in the Body.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O Jeſu, King of Love, fill with thy kind and gentle Spirit all Chriſtian Kings, Princes and Governours. Let no proud Wrath; no malicious Envy; no greedy Covetouſneſs; no turbulent Ambition reign in any of them: Grant that they all, knowing whoſe Miniſters they are, may above all things ſeek thy Honour and Glory: And that they may ſtudy to preſerve the People com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to their Care in Wealth, Peace, and Godlineſs: That they may truly and indifferently adminiſter Juſtice, to the Puniſhment of Wickedneſs and
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:59728:76"/> Vice, and to the Maintenance of thy true Religion and Vertue.</p>
               <p>Eſpecially, O Lord, we intreat thee to regard with pecullar Favour, thy Servants, <hi>WILLIAM</hi> and <hi>MARY,</hi> our moſt Gracious King and Queen. Let thy Wiſdom direct them in all their Adminiſtrations; Thy Almighty Power promote their Good Deſigns, that under them we may be Godly and Quietly Govern'd. Let thy Bounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Goodneſs ſhower upon them abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly all Perſonal Bleſſings, for their Bodies and for their Souls, to their long Proſperity in this Life, and their Everlaſting Happineſs in the next. Since by their Wiſdom and Care, by their Love to Thee, and Goodneſs to Us, with thy Bleſſing upon their En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, we enjoy the happy Liberty of thy Houſe, and theſe thy Bleſſed Ordinances, to the joy and comfort of our Souls, we will never fail to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member them in all our Prayers and Supplications unto thee.</p>
               <pb n="136" facs="tcp:59728:77"/>
               <p> Pour down an Abundance of thy Spirit, we pray thee, O Gracious Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu, upon all Biſhops and Paſtours of thy Church. Repleniſh them all with right and ſound Knowledge, and a true Underſtanding of thy Word. Oh let not their Hearts be govern'd, or their Actions be guided by the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns of Covetouſneſs or Ambition: But do thou poſſeſs and rule them by a great Zeal for thy Glory, and for thy great Deſign the Salvation of Souls: Grant that they may by their Holy Doctrine, and Anſwerable Lives, be mightily ſucceſsfull in turning ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to Righteouſneſs; and that they may ſave Themſelves, and many of thoſe that are committed to their Charge.</p>
               <p>Since my Goodneſs, O Lord, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends not to thee; and thou art a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the receiving of any Advantage by the beſt Returns that I can make for all thy Bounty to me: It ſhall be my Charge and Care to requite thy kindneſs upon thy Servants to whom
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:59728:77"/> I may be profitable. I will love them, O Lord, that love thee, and do all the good I can to thoſe eſpecially that <hi>are of the Houſhold of Faith:</hi> I will gladly relieve the Neceſſities of thy Servants which are made known to me; will Feed the Hungry, Cloath the Naked, Inſtruct the Ignorant, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the Wandering, Viſit the Sick and Impriſoned, Comfort and Help the Weak-hearted, and Vindicate and Aſſiſt the Fatherleſs and Widows in their Diſtreſs, according as I have Opportunity and Power to do ſo. And give me, I beſeech thee, O lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Jeſu, a juſt and large Notion of <hi>the Houſhold of Faith,</hi> that I may not confine this my Charity within too narrow Bounds. Let me be always afraid of reſtraining it within too nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Limits, never of extending it too far among Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>I love thee, O Lord Jeſus, for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſo ſweet and pleaſant a thing as Charity my Duty, and do account even this an Inſtance of thy Charity
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:59728:78"/> to me. If there be any other Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of this Divine Vertue, O Lord, which I have not thought of, I deſire Thee, the great Fountain of Love, to admoniſh me of it, and always to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe me to it. Grant that in the pleaſing Exerciſe of Love I may paſs the time of my ſojourning here in this Malicious, Miſerable World; till I come at length to that Happy One, where ſincere, abundant, and unalter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Love, and Joy, and Glory dwell for ever.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:59728:78"/>
               <head>SECT. XVIII. <hi>PRAYERS for Preparation.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="1" type="prayer">
                  <head>I.</head>
                  <p>O God of Love, Father of all Mercies, and Giver of every good and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Gift. It is thy Command, and I reckon it a kind and a juſt One, That I ſhould Celebrate this Sacrament in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of the Death and Sacrifice of thy dear Son, our onely Saviour and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt; To make me Thankfull for his Love, and for the Benefits of his Paſſion and Death, and that I might be made a Partaker of thoſe Incomparable Benefits: Thou haſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded me in this way to renew my Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with Thee; to declare my ſelf thy Creature and Servant, and bind my ſelf to continue thy Faithfull Servant, and to live as becomes one that had his Being from Thee. O Lord, I muſt acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge it is but too neceſſary for me to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new the Obligations which I am ſo apt to tranſgreſs. I am therefore heartily
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:59728:79"/> willing: I deſire to ſtrengthen the Bonds of Love, that they may hold me the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to my Duty. I would never be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted from the Yoke of thy Service; Oh do not thou caſt me out of it for the ſake of Jeſus Chriſt. And I am willing to remember my dear Saviour's dying Love, to be deeply Affected with it, and therefore to uſe ſo lively a Repreſentation of his Death, as he has provided in this Sacrament. I muſt indeed own my ſelf Infinitely unworthy of ſo great Good, but yet cannot chuſe but be earneſtly deſirous, O Lord, to partake abundantly in the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits and Benefits of my Saviour's Death; There is nothing ſo dear to me as to have all mine Iniquities pardon'd; to recover thy Favour: To enjoy the excellent Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Holy Spirit, and be conſecrated for a Sacred Temple to Him: To receive Earneſts and Pledges, yea, and Fore-taſts of my future Joy and Happineſs: All which are the matchleſs Bleſſings He has purchaſed for me, and which Thou haſt directed thy Church to ſeek and partake of in and by this Sacrament. All this I humbly ſeek and crave, through the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of Jeſus Chriſt my Lord, to whom with the Father and the Holy Ghoſt, be
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:59728:79"/> all Honour and Glory, World without End. </p>
                  <closer>Amen.</closer>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="prayer">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>Almighty and moſt Mercifull God, I bleſs Thee for this Sacrament, and would come to it with a hungring and thirſting Soul. But, alas, how ſhall I, a poor mean Creature, approach thy Majeſty! How ſhall I, a guilty polluted Sinner, dare to approach thy Purity and Holineſs! O Lord, I am Infinitely unworthy to come ſo near Thee: Yet, it ſeems, thou doſt not regard my Unworthineſs, elſe Thou wouldeſt never have invited me. Thou inviteſt poor ſinfull Creatures in General to this Feaſt; thy Gueſts can be none but ſuch: If all therefore that are unworthy to come, ſhould Abſent themſelves, none of us would be there; and thy vaſt and land Preparations would be in vain; I come therefore, moſt Gracious God, in Obedience to thy Command and Invita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: But I will come with the lowlieſt Reverence and Humility, for thou haſt regard unto the Lowly: I will come as a returning Prodigal, for Thou art wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to receive ſuch: I will come, hoping in thy Infinite Mercy; for there is Mercy
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:59728:80"/> with Thee, through Jeſus Chriſt. My great Concern, O Lord, is, that I may be in ſome good meaſure fit to approach Thee, though I can never be worthy; and that I may have and exerciſe thoſe Qualifications in my attendance on Thee, which are ſuitable to this Sacrament, and which Thou requireſt. I have therefore earneſtly endeavour'd to find or form thoſe Qualifications in my ſelf; But, alas, O Lord, I dare not truſt to my own Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aminations or Endeavours. Do Thou, the Heart-ſearching God, examine and try me; do Thou, I pray Thee, prepare me. I fly to thy Grace and Bleſſed In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence: Lord, give me, I pray, what Thou requireſt to be in me. It is my great Encouragement to make this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, that I know I ask herein what Thou art willing to give. Thou, Lord, art always more ready to Hear, than we to Pray; and art wont to give more than either we deſire or deſerve. Thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt I cannot have theſe Qualifications but from Thee: Since therefore Thou haſt commanded me to come poſſeſs'd with Them, I am ſure Thou art willing to give Them. Thou art deſirous we ſhould come prepar'd, and ſuitable Gueſts to this
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:59728:80"/> Heavenly Entertainment; art deſirous to ſee thy Houſe fill'd with ſuch. Fill me then, good Lord, and many other Souls, with thoſe Graces which it becomes us to approach Thee with, for the ſake of Jeſus Chriſt our Mediatour and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate.</p>
                  <closer>Amen.</closer>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="prayer">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>O Lord of Infinite Bounty and Power, I humbly pray Thee, give me a ſincere and unfeigned Repentance for all my Sins: Oh let the Remembrance of them be grievous unto me, the Burden of their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence and Power intolerable. Poſſeſs me with a hearty Shame and Sorrow for that I have ſo baſely and unworthily affronted thy Infinite Majeſty, and put my kind Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour to ſo much grief and ſuffering to ſave me. Poſſeſs me with an earneſt Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of what is ſo diſpleaſing to Thee as my Sins juſtly are; that I may earneſtly and ſteadily endeavour to caſt them from me. Turn Thou my fooliſh Heart from the Love of all Sin, to the Love of Thee. Do Thou, O Lord, who beſt knoweſt all the dark Corners of my Heart, diſcover to me every lurking ſecret Evil, which I have not been able by my Examination
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:59728:81"/> to obſerve; and let it now be brought forth and ſlain before Thee.</p>
                  <p>Increaſe in me, O good Lord, I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly pray, a lively Faith in thy Mercy, through the Merits and Mediation of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Chriſt. Help me firmly to believe thy readineſs to receive, and pardon Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners that repent and return to Thee: To rely with all Aſſurance on the Sacrifice and Attonement of thy Son's precious Death: Raiſe in me the comfortable Hopes of all Mercy and Favour upon that ſure Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation; and grant me to rejoice in Hopes of ſeeing thy Glory.</p>
                  <p>Oh that my Heart may be all on a Flame of Divine Love, even a whole Burnt-offering, when I remember and conſider my Saviour's dying Love to Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. Eſpecially when I ſee him in this Sacrament, as it were evidentiy ſet forth Crucified before Me: When I ſee there his broken Body, and his Blood poured out; and conſider that all this He ſuffer'd for Me. Oh let ſuch a ſight affect me, as it ought to do, beyond all Expreſſion. Oh let it transform me into Love. Let it make ſuch ſtrong and laſting Impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon me, that I may ever afterwards be under the ſweet and mighty Influences
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:59728:81"/> of Love; always be guided by the Laws, and aiming at the Ends of Love. Let Love and Thankfulneſs to Him greatly employ my Soul when I am at this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, and be from thenceforth the great Concern and Buſineſs, the very form and Character of my whole Life for ever.</p>
                  <p>And ſince my Love cannot redound to his Advantage, make it to flow abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly upon thoſe that love Him. Give me a free Heart and Hand, and power to do much good to them. According to my power I purpoſe to Exerciſe my Charity towards them, and towards all Men, in Thought, Word and Deed at this Sacrament. I pray that the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial of my dear Saviour's Love may effectually inſpire me to do ſo: And I purpoſe, and deſire, and pray, that Thou wilt be pleaſed to inable me, to abound in Love and Good Works to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards all Men, through the whole Courſe of my Life.</p>
                  <p>Put, I beſeech Thee, O Lord, my Soul in all reſpects into ſuch a poſture as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes the Remembrance of a Crucified Saviour, that I may be well-pleaſing and accepted with Thee; That thou mayeſt
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:59728:82"/> delight over me to do me good; That I may have Communion with Thee to the Joy and Comfort of my Soul; to the Encreaſe of Spiritual Strength; to the ſecuring of my Perſeverance in Holineſs and Righteouſneſs all my days. All which I humbly ask in the Name of Jeſus Chriſt; and further crave what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is comprehended in his moſt Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Form of Prayer, ſaying,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Our Father which art in Heaven,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <closer>Amen.</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:59728:82"/>
               <head>SECT. XIX. <hi>Directions for a Devout Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour at the Communion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THanks be to God we have ſo good proviſion made by our Church for the Adminiſtration of this Bleſſed Sacrament; That any good Soul may receive it with great Devotion and Comfort, who will but ſeriouſly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to what is appointed to be ſaid and done in that Adminiſtration; as indeed many ſuch Souls, <hi>accuſtomed</hi> to it, have found by very comfortable Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience: Upon which account it were much to be deſired, and very adviſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, That thoſe who are wont to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend this way but once in a Year, when they enter into an Office, would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade themſelves to come more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently to it; That they might do ſo with the more comfort and advantage to their Souls, when that Occaſion re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:59728:83"/> them to do it: For the whole Buſineſs is ſo order'd, that 'tis very Apt and Fit to ſtir up in us the lively and vigorous Exerciſe of all thoſe Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which are required to Attend it. So that the beſt Advice which can be given for our due and profitable Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour at the Holy Communion is this: That the Communicant do very cloſely Attend to what is order'd to be ſaid and done by Him that Miniſters, or by the Communicant Himſelf, while they are upon this Duty.</p>
               <p>But becauſe the Communicants, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially where the Number is great, (as I wiſh it were every-where) will have ſome Spaces wherein they may employ themſelves in ſome private E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jaculations and Devotions; I ſhall not think it contrary to the propoſed Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity of this Book, to afford them ſome ſuch Devout Prayers and Ejaculations as they may uſe; and I ſhall put them in their proper Places. But theſe muſt be commonly very ſhort, that they may not be diverted from joining with the Publick Office.</p>
               <pb n="149" facs="tcp:59728:83"/>
               <p> To begin then, where we uſually be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin this Adminiſtration.</p>
               <p>When He that Miniſters is reading thoſe Sentences of Holy Scripture which are deſign'd to Exhort and Encourage the making our Offerings to Almighty God: While you have your Offering in your Hand, or when you have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven it, ſay,</p>
               <p>O Lord of Heaven and Earth, Maker and Owner of all Things! All that I have and am is from Thee, and all is Thine. Thou doſt give, and Thou haſt right to take and uſe what Thou pleaſeſt of it: I humbly preſent This according to my A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility; as an Acknowledgment of thy right in me, and in all that I have; and of thy Bounty in giving it. I preſent, and I humbly intreat Thee to accept This as a Token and Pledge of the Dedication of my ſelf, and all that I have, to ſerve and honour Thee. Sprinkle me, O Lord Jeſus, and this my Duty with thy preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Blood, and obtain for me, by thy Merits, a great Encreaſe of all Spiritual Gifts and Graces, to thy Glory and my Salvation. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="150" facs="tcp:59728:84"/>
               <p> When the Offerings are all receiv'd, and ſet upon the Altar: He that Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters proceeds to make Interceſſions to God for the Whole State of Chriſt's Church Militant here on Earth: In which it becomes every Devout Soul, as a Living Member of that Church, to join with him, with very hearty Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections.</p>
               <p>After this He proceeds to an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, which is deſign'd to deterr all thoſe from drawing near to this Holy Ordinance, who are conſcious to Themſelves that they have been negligent to prepare for it; and who live in any known Sin. And then it goes on to Encourage thoſe Humble Penitents, and Faithfull Souls, who have been carefull to prepare Them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and to excite in them thoſe Diſpoſitions with which they ought to come. It will be very proper for the Communicant, while the Miniſter is reading this, to join with Him, and to turn it into a Prayer, thus:</p>
               <pb n="151" facs="tcp:59728:84"/>
               <p> O God that ſearcheſt the Hearts, and trieſt the Reins of Men; and who haſt commanded us to come to the Holy Communion of the Body and Blood of our Saviour Chriſt: Thou knoweſt I have diligently Examin'd my ſelf before I would preſume to eat of this Bread, and drink of this Cup; and have endeavour'd, that I might with a true penitent Heart and lively Faith receive this Holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that ſo I may to my great Benefit and Conſolation ſpiritually eat the Fleſh of Chriſt herein, and drink his Blood; that I may be one with Chriſt, and Chriſt with Me: And that I might not receive the ſame unworthily, nor, which I dread to ſpeak, be guilty of the Body and Blood of Chriſt my Saviour, and ſo eat and drink my own Damnation, not conſidering the Lord's Body: That I might not kindle thy Wrath againſt me, but find favour in thy ſight; That I might not provoke Thee to plague me with Temporal Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, but obtain the continuance of ſuch Comforts as I enjoy, and the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowing of ſuch as Thou ſeeſt moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient for me; That I might not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke Thee to cut me off by an untimely
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:59728:85"/> Death, I have, according to the direction of thy Apoſtle, ſeriouſly judg'd my ſelf. <hi>Do not thou enter into Judgment with thy Servant, O Lord, for in thy ſight ſhall no Man living be juſtified.</hi> I have repented my paſt Sins, and do repent of them: I have endeavour'd to be poſſeſt of a lively and ſtedfaſt Faith in Chriſt my Saviour; Lord encreaſe my Faith. I reſolve to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend, by the Aſſiſtance of thy Grace, what-ever Evil I ſhall be convinced of in my Life: And I heartily ſeek thy Favour upon this juſt and reaſonable Condition of being in Charity with all Men. O Lord I forgive, let me be forgiven: And after all, I moſt humbly pray Thee, who alone canſt do it to make me a meet par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of theſe Holy Myſteries. Above all, I give moſt humble and hearty Thanks to God the Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt, for the Redemption of the World, by the Death and Paſſion of our Saviour Chriſt, both God and Man; Who did humble Himſelf even to the Death upon the Croſs for us miſerable Sinners; Who lay in Darkneſs and the ſhadow of Death, that He might make us the Children of God, and Exalt us to Everlaſting Life. I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire at this time with all Thankfulneſs to
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:59728:85"/> remember the Exceeding great Love of our Maſter and only Saviour in his thus Dying for us; and the Innumerable Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits which by his precious Blood-ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding He hath obtain'd to us. I heartily give Him thanks too, for that He hath further ſhown his Love to wretched Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners in his Inſtituting and Ordaining Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Myſteries for Pledges of his Love, that we might have the move full Aſſurance of it, and for a continual Remembrance of his Death to our Great and Endleſs Comfort. To Him therefore with the Father and the Holy Ghoſt, I gave, as I am moſt bounden, continual Thanks, ſubmitting my ſelf wholly to his Holy will and Pleaſure, and purpoſing that I will ſtudy to ſerve Him in true Holineſs and Righteouſneſs all the Days of my Life.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the next place you are to join with the Miniſter with all Humility and true Godly Sorrow in a Confeſſion of Sins, and to receive by Him God's Abſolution.</p>
               <pb n="154" facs="tcp:59728:86"/>
               <p> To the Sentences of Holy Scripture which. He next recites to encourage our Faith and Hope in God, it may be proper to make in your Hearts ſome ſuch Anſwers as theſe.</p>
               <p>To thoſe Words of our Saviour, <hi>Come unto me,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Behold, O Lord, I come: Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, thou Son of <hi>David,</hi> have Mercy up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me.</p>
               <p>To thoſe Words, <hi>God ſo loved the World,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer.</hi> O Father of Mercies, have Mercy upon me, and give me that Faith in thy Son, that I may not Periſh, but have Everlaſting Life.</p>
               <p>To the Words of St. <hi>Paul, This is a true Saying,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Lord, I believe the Truth of this, and thankfully embrace ſo Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant a Truth: O Chriſt, ſave me, one of the chiefeſt of Sinners.</p>
               <p>To the Words of St. <hi>John, If any Man ſin,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="155" facs="tcp:59728:86"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Be Thou, O Jeſus, the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, my Powerfull Advocate with the Father: O Father, accept of his Death as a Propitiation for my Sins.</p>
               <p>To what the Miniſter ſays next, you are to make the Anſwers directed, and to join with Him in the Praiſes and Prayers following.</p>
               <p>After that the Bread and Wine is by the Prayer of Conſecration ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part to repreſent the Body and Blood of Chriſt; and while the Miniſters are receiving, you muſt look upon the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lements with an Holy, Awfull Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and ſadly call to Mind the Scourging, the Buffetings, the Crown of Thorns, the cruel Nails and Spear which wounded and bruiſed, which tore and kill'd the Loving Jeſus: You may remember the more terrible Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings and ſharp Agonies of his Soul; which He endur'd eſpecially when He made his Life an Offering for Sin. And you ſhould call to mind it was your Sins that gave Him all theſe Sufferings and Griefs; that yet He endur'd them
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:59728:87"/> for your Advantage; And He was Scourg'd, that by His ſtripes you might be healed; He ſhed His Blood to ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome you from Hell and Miſery; and died, that He might obtain for you Everlaſting Life and Happineſs. And while the reſt of the Company are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving, if they are a good Number; you will have leiſure, and may very profitably entertain your ſelf with read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over the foregoing Exerciſes of Thankfull Remembrance, Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And in reading them, you may Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe thoſe Graces as you ought to do. If there will not be time to repeat them all, you may do well to chuſe ſome ſuch a one or more of them as is moſt ſuitable to the preſent State, and diſpoſition of your Mind. For the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout Soul may be at one time more taken up in Admiration and Praiſe of the Dying Love of Jeſus Chriſt: At another time it may be eſpecially poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt with a deep Humiliation and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance; at another time it may be elevated with the Hopes and Joys of
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:59728:87"/> Believing; Or engag'd in making Ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Reſolutions of Love, Obedience, and Gratitude to the Great Redeemer: Or in Exerciſes of Charity to the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable and ſinfull World; And your Entertainment at this ſpare time may be choſen accordingly. Only this muſt be adviſed, in relation to this matter, That you ſhould make Obſervation of your ſelf, whether you do not too com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly fix your Meditations upon one and the ſame of theſe Exerciſes, and ſo neglect the reſt: For this muſt not be allow'd; But you muſt conſtrain your ſelf, if need be, to uſe ſometimes one, and ſometimes another of theſe, that ſo you may at times Exerciſe every Grace, and by the Exerciſe encreaſe in all.</p>
               <p>When you go to Receive, and ſee the Miniſter approaching with the Sacred Bread, which repreſents the broken Body of our Lord, look on it, and ſay:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Behold,</hi> my Soul, <hi>the Lamb of God, which taketh away the Sins of the World.</hi>
                  <pb n="158" facs="tcp:59728:88"/> 
                  <hi>Worthy is the Lamb that was ſlain to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Power, and Riches, and Wiſdom, and Strength, and Honour, and Glory, and Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing.</hi> Oh come Lord Jeſus, take poſſeſſion of my Soul, and dwell Thou for ever with me; that I may be the more fit for ſuch a Happineſs, transform me into thy Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, by the renewing of my Mind. Open ye everlaſting Doors of my Heart, that the King of Glory may come in.</p>
               <p>When He delivers it to you, join with Him, and ſay:</p>
               <p>The Body of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, which was given for me, preſerve my Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and Soul unto Everlaſting Life.</p>
               <p>And as you are eating it, ſay within your ſelf:</p>
               <p>O Jeſu, Thou art the Living, and Life, giving Bread, which cometh down from Heaven; which, whoſoever eateth, he ſhall live for ever. Thy Fleſh is Meat indeed, and thy Blood is Drink indeed: On Thee my hungry Soul ſhall feed, by my Faith, with hearty Thankfulneſs. Let me taſt and find, that Thou, Lord, art Gracious; Thou that filleſt the Hungry with good things, repleniſh me abundantly with thy
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:59728:88"/> Grace. Oh let this Divine and Spiritual Food afford me much Spiritual Strength and Refreſhment.</p>
               <p>When He delivers the Cup, join with Him, and ſay:</p>
               <p>The Blood of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, which was ſhed for me, preſerve my Body and Soul unto Everlaſting Life.</p>
               <p>And when you have drank it, ſay:</p>
               <p>Thy Love, O King of Saints, is better than Wine. As the Apple-tree among the Trees of the Wood, ſo is my Beloved among the Sons: We will remember thy Love more than Wine: The Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of thy wondrous Love ſhall be the frequent, and the moſt pleaſant En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment of my Life: Thy Love, O Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu, ſhall comfort me in my Sorrows; ſhall ſtrengthen me in my Weakneſs; ſhall quicken and cure my Sloth, and Backward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to my Duty: Oh let thy Love even transform me into Love. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O Father of Mercies, and of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, whom thou haſt <hi>ſet forth to be a Propitiation through Faith in his Blood,</hi> behold, I beſeech Thee, this precious Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of thy Son! Behold it, I pray Thee,
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:59728:89"/> and turn away from me, thy poor feeble Creature, all the Wrath and Vengeance which my Sins have deſerv'd. This is that on which I firmly and ſolely rely to find favour with Thee; and this is that in which I know. Thou art well-pleaſed: Oh Father of Mercies, have Mercy upon me. Deal always with thy Servant ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thy Mercy; And teach me thy Statutes, that I may hereafter ſerve and pleaſe Thee in Newneſs of Life: And I humbly hope and deſire to be accepted with Thee, through the Merits and Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of thy beloved Son, who died for our Sins, and roſe again for our Juſtification; is now ſet down at thy right hand, and ever lives to make Interceſſion for us. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Taking notice of the Sacrament de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver'd to others, you may thus im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove it.</p>
               <p>Jeſus, the rich and bounteous Lover, has good things in ſtore for as many as come unto Him: Jeſus is able to ſave to the uttermoſt all that come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God by Him. Of his Fulneſs do all we receive, and Grace for Grace. See, my Soul! ſee here thy Maſter's
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:59728:89"/> Bounty and Love! See Him here gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving even Himſelf to His Friends.</p>
               <p>My Soul, if Jeſus ſo lov'd us all, we ought alſo to love one another. This Commandment has He left us, that He, who loves God, ſhould love his Brother alſo. Study, then, what Offices of Love and Kindneſs it may lie in thy Power to do to any of theſe thy fellow Communicants, and reſolve upon it, for the Kind Jeſus will take it as even done to Him. If thou love Him truly, thou muſt needs love thoſe whom He loves: Thou muſt pity them in all their Diſtreſſes, Spiritual and Temporal, whom He has pitied in their Miſery at ſo coſtly a Rate: Thou muſt learn to forgive thoſe whom He forgives: Thou muſt be liberal accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to thy Power, and their Neceſſities to thoſe whom thou ſeeſt the Objects of his Bounteous Love. And eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally thou muſt charge thy ſelf not to Hate, not to do any Deſpite or Injury to any of theſe; for even that too would He take as done to Himſelf:
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:59728:90"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="161" facs="tcp:59728:90"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="162" facs="tcp:59728:91"/> Thou muſt not deſpiſe any of theſe for their mean Condition in this World: He may have made the poor of this World rich in Faith: Thou muſt not envy nor grudge at any of them whom the Providence of God has favour'd more than He has done Thee in the Bleſſings of this World. Thou muſt take heed always that thy Carriage be not a Scandal and Occaſion of Sin to any of theſe; that thou deſtroy not Him whom Chriſt died for. And bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be thy Name, O Lord, for theſe ſweet and pleaſant Laws. I willingly bind my ſelf, O Jeſu, to Obſerve theſe thy Laws of Love. Oh thou great Pattern of Love, learn me to Love.</p>
               <p>O Kindeſt Jeſu, thy Body was broken<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and is divided amongſt us to unite us to Thee, and to one another. Let it be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us a Common Incentive of Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Charity: Let it be, in its Effects, Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Spirit among us, a Bond of Peace, and all Righteouſneſs of Life in our Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage one towards another. O Thou the Great Fountain of Love, pour it abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:59728:91"/> into my Heart, and into the Hearts of all thy Faithfull People; That we may abound in Love one towards another; and by thus bearing thy Glorious Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter and Likeneſs, in Love, may ſhow to all Men that we are indeed thy Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When all have Communicated, and the Miniſter begins the Prayers that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main, you are to leave off all private Devotions, and to join with Him and the Congregation to the End.</p>
               <p>After He has pronounced the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, you may privately ſay:</p>
               <p>To Him that loved us, and waſh'd us from our Sins in his own Blood, and hath made us Kings and Prieſts unto God and his Father: To Him with the Father and the Holy Ghoſt, be Glory and Dominion for ever, and ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then riſing from your Knees, kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and courteouſly ſalute your Fellow Communicants at the parting of the Congregation.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="devotions">
            <pb n="164" facs="tcp:59728:92"/>
            <head>Some Private Devotions at Home, after the Communion.</head>
            <div n="20" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XX. <hi>A Meditation on the Communion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>OH my Soul, ſeriouſly conſider how thou haſt been honour'd, how thou haſt been entertain'd in the Houſe of God this Day! Thou haſt been a Gueſt to the King of Saints, the Lord of Life and Glory: Divine Love has been thy Heavenly Entertainment, and Man did eat Angel's Food. Thy Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, thy Friend has brought<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Thee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Banqueting-Houſe, his Banner over Thee was Love. Thou canſt not ſurely very ſoon forget the Pleaſures of this Feaſt: Has it not left behind it a very pleaſing reliſh? Has it not put thy Mouth quite out of taſt towards the things of this World? It is very
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:59728:92"/> fit that it ſhould do ſo: It would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Thee for ſome time after this to account this World's beſt Delights to be but four and infipid; and certainly, if thou meditate upon the good En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment thou haſt had, it will be ſo.</p>
               <p>Jeſus, the Glorious Son of God, was Maſter of the Feaſt thou haſt been at ſo lately, and He was Himſelf the Feaſt. Jeſus prepar'd it out of Love to Thee. And becauſe His great Love could not (as we may eaſily imagine) provide any thing better, He provided Himſelf to be thy rich and coſtly En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment. He has feaſted thee with His Body and Blood. He has, in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving thee that Bread and Wine, which was by the Miniſter, according to his appointment, conſecrated and ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part to repreſent His broken Body, and His Blood ſhed for Mankind, made thee a partaker of the Spiritual Bleſſings and Benefits of His Death and Paſſion. Oh how great Things has He then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow'd on thee! Where canſt thou
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:59728:93"/> find again ſuch Entertainment? What Enjoyments of this poor World could afford it? And if He has given thee never ſo much of this World, He has herein given thee that which is of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely greater value: And if He has given thee but little of this World, thou haſt no reaſon to complain of Him who has been ſo free, ſo bounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to thee in ſo much better things. Say then to Him, Oh how plenteous, how rich is thy Goodneſs, Lord, which Thou haſt in reſerve for thoſe that fear Thee, and that hope in thy Mercy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
               <p>He has treated Thee with the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of all thy Sins, however numerous, however heinous and guilty. Canſt thou forbear to admire and praiſe ſo great a Favour? Is it not wondrous that ſo vaſt a Debt ſhould be ſo freely forgiven thee? Does not this Forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs reſtore thee to the Almighty Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and Love of God? And give thee leave to ask, and ground to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, from Reconciled Heaven, all that is good for thee, and neceſſary to thy
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:59728:93"/> Salvation? Oh ſay then, Bleſs the Lord, O my Soul: All that is within me praiſe his Holy Name; Who hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed my Life from Deſtruction, who forgiveth all my Sins: Who crown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth me with Loving-kindneſs and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Mercies: Oh, Bleſſed is the Man whoſe Tranſgreſſion is forgiven, whoſe Sin is cover'd: Bleſſed, O Lord Jeſus is the Man that putteth his Truſt in Thee.</p>
               <p>He hath beſtow'd on thee, my Soul, his Holy Spirit to dwell with, and to ſanctifie thee, to fill thee with all Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Graces: To heal all the Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of thy Soul, thy uneaſie, ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Diſtempers; to make thee tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and pleaſant to thy ſelf, and ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and well-pleaſing to Him. Oh happy Souls, that are the Temples of this Holy Spirit! Where He dwells, all things ſhall be in a beautifull Order; all things compoſed and calm, and peacefull; all full of Joy: There is a Peace which the World cannot give, and a Joy unſpeakable and full of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:59728:94"/> In them Heaven dwells already; They ſhall be acquainted with its In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable Felicities here on Earth; and they are ſeal'd hereby to the Day of Redemption.</p>
               <p>Thy loving Lord, then, has given thee at this Feaſt, too, the Pledges and Earneſts of Future Glory and Bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. He has even united thee to Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf after a wonderfull manner: He looks on thee as a Member of his own Body; Has made thee Partaker in his Death, and intends thee to partake in his Reſurrection. He will not leave thy Soul in Hell, nor ſuffer thy Dead Body to lie always under Diſſolution. He will <hi>ſhew thee the Path of Life,</hi> and thou ſhalt dwell <hi>at his right hand, where are Pleaſures for ever-more:</hi> Thou ſhalt dwell in His preſence, where is <hi>fulneſs of Joy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oh how like a God has thy glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and kind Saviour entertain'd thee! None could ever beſtow ſuch things on thee but He. Thou haſt been treated as a Favourite of Heaven, who canſt
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:59728:94"/> not chuſe but acknowledge thy ſelf a poor, vile, and contemptible Sinner. All theſe Bleſſings and Favours He hath conferr'd upon thee, and given thee in this Sacrament ſenſible Pledges and Tokens of them; though thou art unworthy of the very meaneſt and the commoneſt of his Gifts to Mankind. Aſſure thy ſelf it was not for any Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit or Worthineſs in thee that he has been ſo Bountifull, but of his own free Motion! There is nothing of Debt in his Love, but thou muſt look upon it as altogether Obligation.</p>
               <p>And now, my Soul, thou muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider too the mighty Obligation he has laid upon thee. Thou art able to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, to do nothing in return for his Love, but what he has infinitely ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd thee to. Should ſuch a Love as this ever be forgotten; or rather ſhould'ſt thou not reſolve that thou wilt always retain a gratefull Sence of it: And that ſuch a Love ſhall be the greateſt Joy and the ſweeteſt Delight of thy Life: That ſuch a Love ſhall
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:59728:95"/> make an entire Conqueſt of thee; and make thee ſubject to the pleaſant Laws of it, through the whole Courſe of thy Life. Thou canſt not ſure, for ſhame, think of a leſs return, than to give up thy ſelf to Him; To live to Him that died for thee; To ſtudy and love what will pleaſe Him, and do it in all things. No; thou canſt not think of any thing leſs than of being His Servant, who has bought thee with ſo great a Price! Who has ranſom'd thee from Hell and Everlaſting Miſery, and that by his own cruel Sufferings and accurſed Death.</p>
               <p>And will it ever become thee, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thou, after thou haſt conſider'd the cruel Sufferings of Jeſus for thy ſake, to ſhrink or murmure at Sufferings, or guiltily decline them? Wilt thou pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to be Follower, a Diſciple of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, and yet not be able to endure any thing grievous or inconvenient? Has he ſuffer'd very grievous things for thee, worſe by far than thou art able, or wilt ever be call'd to ſuffer for his
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:59728:95"/> ſake? And wilt thou ſuffer nothing for Him? Was his way to Heaven en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>combred with ſharp Thorns, and will it become thee to murmure if thine be not ſtrow'd with Roſes? Was the Great and Glorious Jeſus deſpiſed in the World, and muſt thou be mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſpected and honour'd? Was Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, the Son of <hi>David,</hi> (a rich and mighty King) mean and poor, and will nothing ſerve thee but to be vaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſuperfluouſly rich? For ſhame, my Soul! Theſe Deſires cannot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come thee. It is enough for the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple that he be as his Maſter; and ſurely 'tis an Honour that the Servant be as his Lord. If thou wilt be a Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lower of Jeſus, thou muſt expect, as the World hated Him, ſaw no form nor comelineſs in Him; ſo it will hate, and it will ſcorn thee; It will not ſee any thing to admire in thee: Conſider the Sufferings of Jeſus, and harden thy ſelf; Learn from Him to deſpiſe the Inconveniences of this Life; learn to deſpiſe its Allurements. From his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differency
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:59728:96"/> towards it, 'tis thy Duty and thy Honour to be very Indifferent too. And this, as all thy Duty, thou wilt find pleaſant upon the trial of it, and a reward to it ſelf. This will give thee an invincible compoſure and peace of Mind, a happy Command and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of thy ſelf under all the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſſitudes and Changes of this mutable uncertain World.</p>
               <p>Conſider further, my Soul; Has He bleſt thee with the Pardon of all thy Sins? And does not this oblige thee to take the utmoſt care that thou Sin no more? Know, he that has had much forgiven him, ſhould love much; and Love will not let thee do any thing willingly, that is ſo diſpleaſing and hatefull to the Kind and Holy Jeſus, as the leaſt Sin would be. Conſider; Thy Sins were pardon'd to oblige thee to forſake them for ever; and this does greatly oblige thee to it: It were hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid and monſtrous Ingratitude, then, if the Pardon of what is paſt ſhould encourage thee to begin a new ſcore.
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:59728:96"/> Oh, abhorr the Thoughts of this, and reckon thou art oblig'd to live with great Care of thy ſelf, to take great Heed to thy Ways, to ſhun even the Appearances of Evil, to abhorr and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void, as much as thou canſt, all Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations to Wickedneſs.</p>
               <p>Conſider, my Soul, the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is come to dwell with Thee; to Conſecrate Thee to be a Sacred Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to Himſelf! Oh Divine Gueſt! Oh how great is thy Honour and thy Happineſs! Wilt thou not let Him know that thou doſt account it both? Wilt thou not ſtudy to be eaſie to ſuch a Gueſt? To ſhow him the greateſt reſpects? Know then, that he muſt Rule in thy Heart; He muſt be, not in Complement only, but, in Reality Maſter of the Houſe He is Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able enough, ſurely, to have ſuch Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect done Him: And it will be thy Advantage to give it Him. He will order all things better there than ever thou could'ſt do without Him. And thou muſt take care that thou never
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:59728:97"/> admit thy Luſts or vile Affections a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; He will not dwell with ſuch vile Company; If thou would'ſt retain the Happineſs of his Preſence, they muſt be for ever baniſh'd from thy Soul: And ſure it ſhould be very eaſie for thee to ſee 'tis not fit that they ſhould be allow'd ſo much as a Competition with Him.</p>
               <p>Conſider too how it becomes a Soul to live, that is deſign'd an Inhabitant of Heaven; that is already made free of the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> which is above. Should you not now conform your Manners to that bright Company? Should you not conſider what a kind of Life they liv'd when they were here on Earth; and ſet your ſelf to follow Them, as they were Followers of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus? The Vertues which were ſo emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent in their Lives, muſt alſo ſhine in yours. They were not many of them Emperours, and Kings, and Queens on Earth, becauſe that Fortune, ſhall I ſay, or rather that Burden, falls to the ſhares of but few among Mankind:
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:59728:97"/> Neither were they, it may be, many of them vaſtly rich, and more than they needed to be; But, which is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and of more Advantage to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves than either of theſe, They were poor in Spirit; They were humble and meek; They were temperate and ſober; They were very good and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull; All their Zeal and Concern was to Advance the Glory of God. Theſe are the ſteps thou muſt tread in; This the Way thou muſt follow, to follow them to Bliſs; Thou canſt not come to their End in any contrary Way: Thou muſt <hi>not be conform'd to this World, but be transformed by the Renewing of thy Mind.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thou muſt not eagerly hunt after the Pleaſures, the Wealth and the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferments of this World. It would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come thee to be ever very Indifferent towards them, as having already taſted and enjoy'd far better Things than they: What is capable to afford thee incomparably more pleaſure and ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction: And eſpecially would this
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:59728:98"/> become thee, as being entitled to far better things: To more durable and uſefull Riches, more ſolid and laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Pleaſures, and to far higher Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities and Preferments Theſe, thy Saviour and Friend, has given thee Pledges and Aſſurances of at this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament; and theſe He will beſtow at the Laſt Day to thoſe that Love and Fear Him.</p>
               <p>For thou mayeſt expect that this Jeſus, whoſe humble Sufferings and Death thou haſt now Commemorated, will come again in Glory, with the Hoſts of Glorious Angels attending Him, to Judge both the Quick and the Dead: He will come to <hi>take Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, in Flames of Fire, on them that Obey not his Goſpel</hi> And will come to reward all his faithfull Servants, to be glorified and admired for his Bounty and Rewards to all them that Believe. Oh conſider well, my Soul, that Awfull, Certain Day; And ſuch as thou would'ſt then be found, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour now to be; If this Life be dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:59728:98"/> employ'd in thy Maſter's Work; the performance of thoſe Duties which belong to thy Station, and Calling, and Relations; He will then ſay to thee, <hi>Well done good and faithfull Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, enter thou into thy Maſter's joy.</hi> It will be more to thy advantage, then, to have denied thy ſelf now for thy Maſter's Honour and Service, than to have indulg'd and pleas'd thy ſelf in all things. It will be of greateſt advantage to thee, then, to be found to have been Sober and Temperate, and Good, and Righteous, and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious: When all the Honours, and all the Favour and Applauſe of that Day will be given to ſuch; And no other Differences among Men ſhall be regarded, but their Differences in theſe things. Be ſure, my Soul, it will not then repent thee, what-ever it does now coſt to gain the Rewards and Honour of that Day. Reſolve firmly, then, for a Good and Holy Life; Be never a-weary of Well-do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, for there is an Everlaſting Reſt
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:59728:99"/> which ſhall receive thee at the End of it, and the time before thou wilt reach it is but ſhort. Be not diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged by any Difficulties thou mayeſt meet with; If thou wilt boldly ſtrive, thou ſhalt overcome them all, through Chriſt ſtrengthening thee: To whom with the Father and the Holy Ghoſt, One Ever-bleſſed God, be all Honour and Glory, World without End.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
               <pb n="179" facs="tcp:59728:99"/>
               <head>SECT. XXI. <hi>PRAYERS for a Suitable Converſation.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="1" type="prayer">
                  <head>I.</head>
                  <p>OGod, the Strength of all them that put their Truſt in Thee; Mercifully accept my Prayers; and becauſe through the Weakneſs of our Mortal Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, we can do no good Thing without Thee, grant me the Help of thy Grace, that in keeping thy Commandments I may pleaſe Thee both in Will and Deed, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
                  <closer>Amen.</closer>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="prayer">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>OLord, the Fountain of all Power and Might, grant, I beſeech Thee, to me thy Servant, Grace to withſtand the Temptations of the World, the Fleſh, and the Devil; And with a pure Heart and Mind to follow and ſerve Thee the Onely true and living God; And let me be accepted with Thee in all my Service, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="prayer">
                  <pb n="180" facs="tcp:59728:100"/>
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>OAlmighty God, who alone canſt Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the unruly Wills and Affections of ſinfull Men, Grant unto me thy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, that I may love the Things which Thou Commandeſt, and deſire thoſe Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Things which Thou doſt promiſe; That ſo among the ſundry and manifold Changes of this World, my Heart may ſurely there be fixed, where true Joys are to be found, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="prayer">
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <p>LOrd of all Power and Might, who art the Authour and Giver of all Good Things; Graft in my Heart the Love of thy Name; Encreaſe in me true Religion; Nouriſh me in all Goodneſs, and of thy Great Mercy keep me in the ſame, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="prayer">
                  <head>V.</head>
                  <p>O Lord, who haſt taught us; that all our Doings, without Charity, are nothing worth: Send thy Holy Spirit, I beſeech Thee, and pour into my Heart that moſt Excellent Gift of Charity, the
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:59728:100"/> very Bond of Peace, and of all Vertues; without which, whoſoever liveth, is Dead before Thee. Grant this for thy Onely Son Jeſus Chriſt's ſake. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="prayer">
                  <head>VI.</head>
                  <p>ALmighty God, who haſt given thy Onely, Son to be unto us both a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice for Sin, and alſo an Example of Godly Life: Give me Grace that I may always moſt Thankfully accept that his Ineſtimable Benefit, and alſo daily en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour my ſelf to follow the Bleſſed Steps of his moſt Holy Life, through the ſame Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="prayer">
                  <head>VII.</head>
                  <p>GRant, I beſeech Thee, Almighty God, that like as I do believe thy Onely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>begotten Son, our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, to have Aſcended into the Heavens; ſo I may alſo in Heart and Mind thither aſcend, and with Him continually dwell, who liveth and reigneth with Thee and the Holy Ghoſt, One God, World without End.</p>
                  <closer>Amen.</closer>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="prayer">
                  <pb n="182" facs="tcp:59728:101"/>
                  <head>VIII.</head>
                  <p>MAy the Peace of God, which paſſeth all Underſtanding, keep my Heart and Mind in the Knowledge and Love of God, and of his Son Jeſus Chriſt our Lord; And the Bleſſing of God Almighty, the Father, the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt, be upon me and remain with me always.</p>
                  <closer>Amen.</closer>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="prayer">
                  <head>IX.</head>
                  <p>GLory be to the Father, and to the Son, and to the Holy Ghoſt: As it was in the Beginning, is, now, and ever ſhall be, World without End.</p>
                  <closer>Amen.</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="section">
               <pb n="183" facs="tcp:59728:101"/>
               <head>SECT. XXII. <hi>A PRAYER of Recollection.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THIS contains the Sum of this Book, and is made fit to be uſed after the reading any parts of it in the Family or Cloſet.</p>
               <p>O Moſt Great and Glorious God! Lord of Heaven and Earth, Infinite in Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty and Glory, and in thy Greatneſs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearchable. All things that are, do derive from Thee, the Fountain of Beings, all their Excellency, and all their Power. Thou art worthy of the greateſt Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence from the Higheſt Angels; worthy of our Godly Fear and moſt Awfull Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations; art Exalted in thy Greatneſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all our Bleſſing and Praiſe. And as thy Greatneſs is Infinite, ſo is alſo thy Goodneſs; which Thou haſt exerciſed in a manner ſuitable to thy Excellent Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: For Thou art in all things like thy ſelf, and there is none beſides Thee like unto Thee. In wondrous Wiſdom and Goodneſs haſt Thou made the World,
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:59728:102"/> bounteouſly communicating Being and Happineſs among thy Creatures. But thy Goodneſs has peculiarly ſhown it ſelf in thy dealing with Mankind, and appear'd in amazing Glories. It appears within us, and in all things that are round about us. Thou haſt made Man a Noble Creature, little lower than the Angels. Thou didſt Endow Him with thy Glorious Image in Righteouſneſs and true Holineſs. Thou Crowned'ſt Him with Honour and Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, giving Him Dominion over the Works of thy Hands. Thou haſt built this Beautious World for his Habitation, and plentifully furniſh'd it with all things neceſſary and delightfull to Him. All our Sences preſent us with many Inſtances of thy Goodneſs to us, the Earth is full of it; Day unto Day uttereth Speech, and Night unto Night ſheweth the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of This. We cannot without the greateſt, and the moſt wilfull Blindneſs, fail to ſee it; nor without the moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy and diſingenuous Ingratitude, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get or neglect to Acknowledge it.</p>
               <p>But this, O Lord, is that which we muſt, with Shame and Self-abhorrence, accuſe our ſelves of. All thy Goodneſs, and the Obligations of it, were ſoon forgotten by
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:59728:102"/> our Firſt Parents, and they rebell'd againſt Thee: And we are their true and vile Off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring, going aſtray from the Womb, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in Enmity againſt Thee, and deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing thy Commandments. All the Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs of the World, and the Affronts Thou haſt receiv'd from it, Thou didſt foreſee; and yet of thy great Patience and Forbearance didſt ſpare our Firſt Parents, and permit Them to propagate their baſe and corrupt Nature! And this gives us occaſion, O Lord, to reflect upon the greateſt and moſt glorious Exerciſe of thy Goodneſs to Mankind. When we were all guilty before Thee, and Obnoxious to thy Eternal Wrath; And thy Honour, and thy Juſtice did require our utter Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection and Perdition. Yet even then did thy Wiſdom and Goodneſs contrive and afford us a Way and Means of Salvation: And thy Infinite Greatneſs, though ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly Affronted, did condeſcend to a Concern to ſave us; And a way was found out ſuitable to thy Greatneſs, and our Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity. Even then did God the Father ſo love the World, that He gave his Onely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>begotten Son, that whoſoever Believes in Him ſhould not Periſh, but have Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Life: And then did God the Son,
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:59728:103"/> in his Infinite Compaſſion to Mankind, offer Himſelf to be our Mediatour; And He undertook to purchaſe for us the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Favour which we had loſt at the Coſt of his own Abaſement, in taking our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and of dying a Sacrifice for the Sins of Men. Oh how unwearied, Lord, has thy Kindneſs and Mercy been towards us! And how odious and deteſtable are all our Tranſgreſſions againſt Thee! When we conſider Thee, O Lord, and the Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which Thou haſt laid upon us, we are even confounded to think of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Vileneſs and Enormity of our Sins. We are therefore forced, O Lord, to abhorr our ſelves; We humble, we a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſe our ſelves before Thee. We acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge thy greateſt Diſpleaſure againſt us to be Juſt and Righteous; and muſt own, that we have deſerv'd Thou ſhould'ſt throw us into the Everlaſting Fire which is prepar'd for the Devil and his Angels. But, Bleſſed be thy Name, there is Mercy with Thee, and Thou art, through the Undertaking of our Bleſſed Mediatour, a God forgiving Iniquity, Tranſgreſſion and Sin. We praiſe Thee, we magnifie Thee, O Lord, for thine Ineſtimable Love in the Redemption of the World by our Lord
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:59728:103"/> Jeſus Chriſt. Glory be to the Father, and to the Son, and to the Holy Ghoſt, for this wonderfull Favour and Relief in our low and deſperate Condition. Encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, O Father, by the Sacrifice of thy Son, and relying upon the Merits of it, we return unto Thee: We deſire to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to our Duty. We gladly and thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully accept of the new Offers of Grace and Favour with Thee, which Thou art pleaſed to make us; We ſubmit to the gentle and eaſie Terms thou requireſt of us, and we humbly ſeek thy Favour upon thoſe Conditions. We were, O Lord, by the kind Diſpenſation of thy Providence, in our early Infancy, dedicated to Thee, and engag'd in that Happy Covenant, which Thou affordeſt us as the Way of our Salvation: But we muſt with ſhame confeſs, that we have broken this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and liv'd in too great Neglect of it; and have added to the other Heinouſneſs and Wickedneſs of our vile Sins, the great Guilt of breaking our Vows and Promiſes to Thee. As ſenſible of our unworthy Behaviour, again, O Lord, we deſire to renew thoſe Bonds, and we earneſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire they may be ſo confirm'd by this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newal of them, as that they may never
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:59728:104"/> be broken any more. We renounce this wicked World, our own corrupt Nature, and thine Adverſary the Devil; We pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe not to ſuffer our ſelves to follow, nor be led by them. We will receive, O Lord, what Thou requireſt us to believe; And we devote our ſelves to keep and obey thy Holy, Juſt and Good Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, through the whole Courſe of our Lives: To be always under the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence and Power of Love to Thee, and to our Neighbours: To love Thee with all our Heart, with all our Soul, and with all our Might; and our Neighbour as our ſelves. O Father of Mercies, graciouſly accept of our Repentance, and return un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Thee: Look upon the Death of thy Son, and turn from us all thy Wrath: Juſtifie us freely by thy Grace; Pardon all our Sins upon the account of it; take us into thy Service, and grant that we may ever hereafter pleaſe Thee in New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Holineſs of Life.</p>
               <p>Jeſus, Thou Son of God, have Mercy upon us, O Chriſt hear us; be Thou our Advocate with thy Father! By thy Holy Nativity and Circumciſion; by thy Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritorious Croſs and Paſſion; by thy Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Death and Burial; by thy Glorious
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:59728:104"/> Reſurrection and Aſcenſion take us into thy Care and Protection: Thou that haſt done all theſe things for us, have Mercy upon us: O be Thou <hi>Jeſus</hi> to us, and ſave us from our Sins: Give us, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to thy promiſe, to them that receive Thee, the Glorious Priviledge to become the Sons of God: We accept of Thee, O Lord, as a King to Rule us, and will ſtudy to know and endeavour to Obey thy Commands: We earneſtly deſire thy Teaching as our Great Prophet; and will receive and comply with thy Divine In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, however contrary they are to the corrupt Byaſs of our Nature, and our Love of this World. Lord, we purpoſe to conform our ſelves to them by the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of thy Excellent Example, and not to be conformed to this World. And we will always acknowledge our utter unworthineſs of the leaſt Good, and place all our Hopes in thy Merits and Interceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as our Great High Prieſt. O let us find by the good ſucceſs of all our Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Addreſſes, that Thou haſt Compaſſion on our Miſeries, and doſt ever live to make Interceſſion for us.</p>
               <p>But, alas, we have promiſed and reſolv'd more than we are able to perform with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:59728:105"/> the Influence and Aſſiſtance of thy Good Spirit. We therefore Addreſs our ſelves to Thee, O Bleſſed Spirit: Come down, we beſeech Thee, into our Hearts; repleniſh us abundantly with thy Grace; let us become thy Sacred Conſecrated Temples, and do thou evermore dwell in us: Baniſh and purge out of us for ever all that is contrary and diſpleaſing to Thee. Teach us, that denying all ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and worldly Luſts, we may live ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berly, and righteouſly, and godly in this preſent World. Write thy Law in our Hearts, that we may never depart from it. Increaſe and maintain our Faith; In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe and continue our Love; Cheriſh all Grace in us; and cauſe us to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere in Holineſs, and Vertue, and Well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing, to the End of our Lives. Keep us in the Knowledge and Love of God, and of his Son Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. We purpoſe, O Holy Spirit, duly to wait for thy Bleſſed ſaving Influences in a diligent attendance on thy Sacred Ordinances, the Word and Sacraments: Oh let us be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways in due fitneſs to attend them, when the happy Opportunities of doing ſo are afforded us; and let them be always bleſt to us, and be effectual to promote our San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification, and Salvation.</p>
               <pb n="191" facs="tcp:59728:105"/>
               <p>[Inſert this when this Prayer is uſed in the Morning.]</p>
               <p>We give Thanks to the God of all Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies for the ſafe Protection, the quiet and comfortable Reſt of the laſt Night: We devote this Day and all our Lives to thy Service, in the Duties which Thou giveſt us to do; Aſſiſt us mercifully, O Lord, in all, and Accept us in Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>[Inſert this when this Prayer is uſed at Night.]</p>
               <p>Enlighten our dark Souls, we beſeech Thee, O Lord, with all the Knowledge that is neceſſary to our Salvation: Fill us with Devout Affections, and let thy Love always poſſeſs and rule us: Be Thou, we pray, our Protection this Night from all the Perils and Dangers of it.</p>
               <p>May the Grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the Love of God the Father; and the Communion of the Holy Ghoſt, be with us all henceforth for evermore.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
               <closer>
                  <hi>Our Father which,</hi> &amp;c.</closer>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:59728:106"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Books printed for</hi> B. Aylmer.</head>
            <p>SIX Sermons: One of Stedfaſtneſs in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; Two of Family Religion; Three of the Education of Children; and One of the Advantages of an Early Piety.</p>
            <p>A Perſwaſive to Frequent Communion in the Holy Sacrament of the Lord's Supper. In <hi>Octavo.</hi> Price 3 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Both by his Grace, <hi>John,</hi> late Lord Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Canterbury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Four Laſt Things: <hi>viz.</hi> Death, Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Heaven, and Hell: Practically Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd and Apply'd, in ſeveral Diſcourſes. By <hi>William Bates,</hi> D. D. Recommended as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to be given at Funerals.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>Books Publiſht by the Author of this.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Reform'd Devotions</hi> in Meditations, Hymns and Petitions for Every day in the Week, and every Holy-day in the Year.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Excellent Woman,</hi> deſcrib'd by her True Characters and their Oppoſites; being part of a Tranſlation out of French.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Family Devotions,</hi> for Sunday-Evenings throughout the Year; being Practical Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, with Suitable Prayers: Vol. I. II. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining each Thirteen Sermons: The other Two, intended to make a Sett for the whole Year, are almoſt finiſht, and deſign'd to be committed to the Preſs ſoon after <hi>Chriſtmaſs,</hi> to be Publiſht together: Printed for <hi>John Wyat</hi> at the Roſe in St. <hi>Paul's Church-Yard.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:59728:106"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
